<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>arponr</title>
    <description>blog by arpon</description>
    <link>http://www.arponr.com</link>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 25 Jul 2015 14:34:51 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://www.arponr.com/feed.xml" rel="self"/>
    
    <item>
      <title>The insect and the M.D.</title>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;It’s two o’clock in the suburban afternoon. A grey sky hangs low outside, whispering in the back of everyone’s mind re looming rainfall. Miscellaneous questions are caught in the whispers and whirl forward into consciousness, landing one after another in a paralyzing mess, like piles of crisp dead leaves you’ve tucked against the curb being scattered back over your lawn by gusts of wind. Are the cushions on the patio chairs out? Does the garden need to be humanly watered? Should that errand be run now or postponed until the rain has passed? The rain looms forever ahead in possibility and everything is grey.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;‘Do you want to go to Trader Joe’s?’&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;‘Yeah sure.’&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The world beneath the pregnant sky is hung together in a delicate mechanical balance, everything in rigid expectation of broken water. We glide through it towards Trader Joe’s, trying to perturb nothing. One instant of the drive stands out from the rest: an insect touches down on our windshield, an anxious rain-sensing wiper flinches, and the poor insect is jettisoned the same moment it lands. But the wiper, realizing its error, quickly restores the balance, and the rain cordially holds off.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rain finally begins to fall on the return drive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;‘What is this car doing?’&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the passenger seat, my eyes refocus and I see an old Mercedes sedan proceeding tortoise-like in front of us. The license plate has only five digits, prefixed by the letters ‘M.D.’ and hovering above the word ‘Physician’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;‘I guess it’s a super old doctor.’&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;‘Or his wife.’&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;‘Hey the wife could be the doctor.’&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;‘That’s true. The hair is short though. Is it a man or a woman? I can’t tell. Can you see anything?’&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;‘No the rain’s in the way.’&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hollows in the shape of the genderless M.D.’s identity are slowly bored into our minds as we’re (barely) lead along this single-laned road. With each drawn out meter the rain thickens and the hollows deepen. Things, and time, begin to feel viscous.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The drive’s penultimate turn grants us at last a road with a second lane, though only briefly, the two lanes merging just past the drive’s final stoplight. We slide over from behind the tortoise into the other lane, hoping to pass it and discern the M.D. while the lanes merge. But we lose ground during the maneuver. At the red light, our car is third in its lane and the tortoise second in its.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;‘I think we still can pass, right?’&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;‘It all depends on the car in front of us now, and it doesn’t look too good from the gap between it and the first car.’&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Her assessment turns out to be accurate. Beneath the green light, in a terrible display of patience, the car in front of us allows the M.D. to pull ahead of it. The distance between our questions and their answers increases measurably, palpably, hope-witheringly. I peer into the bottomless hollow and imagine a dry stone well. Is somebody down there? The darkness is impenetrable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We make our way through the hilly stretch between that final stoplight and the final turn. In every moment fresh grids of raindrops pack our windshield and are immediately jettisoned, between which we catch glimpses of the tortoise two cars away, still pulling us through mud. We roll down to a halt at the floor of the final valley. As we turn into our neighborhood, we watch the Mysterious Driver slip away into the grey, slow and steady amidst grids of rain, forever ahead in possibility.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Jul 2015 17:45:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <link>http://www.arponr.com/insect-md</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.arponr.com/insect-md</guid>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Characters in global equivariant homotopy theory</title>
      <description>
</description>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Mar 2015 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <link>http://www.arponr.com</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.arponr.com/senior-thesis</guid>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Vector fields and the J-homomorphism</title>
      <description>
</description>
      <pubDate>Fri, 09 May 2014 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <link>http://www.arponr.com</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.arponr.com/vfields</guid>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Defining the cotangent complex</title>
      <description>
</description>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Dec 2013 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <link>http://www.arponr.com</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.arponr.com/quillen-cotangent</guid>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Dold-Kan correspondence</title>
      <description>
</description>
      <pubDate>Sat, 26 Oct 2013 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <link>http://www.arponr.com</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.arponr.com/doldkan</guid>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Numbers at Google</title>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This is a post about some numbers that I saw at work one day during my
internship at Google. I present them to you without further ado.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;21:&lt;/strong&gt; I got to run a job with 21 terabytes of input. &lt;em&gt;Tera&lt;/em&gt;. And
that’s compressed.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;10000000000:&lt;/strong&gt; 21 TB means I got to compute statistics on data
sets of size greater than 10 billion. &lt;em&gt;Billion&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;3:&lt;/strong&gt; It took fewer than 3 hours to run that job. I love MapReduce
and resources.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;23:&lt;/strong&gt; Later on, after realising I had made some stupid mistakes, I
needed to run that job again (and because it felt so damn cool the
first time, and I could, so why not). Anyway it turns out the data
was on some machines on the East Coast, and the job was running on
machines on the West Coast. That’s efficiency. Well so I (and, by
“I”, I mean someone else on my team who actually knew what he was
doing) managed to get the job running next door to the data. And for
ten minutes or so, that 21 TB was being sent to the job at more than
23 gigbatyes per second. &lt;em&gt;Giga&lt;/em&gt;. Holy bandwidth, batman.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So it turns out working at Google indeed has perks. Those numbers are
all due to some really smart people that work (or have worked)
here. That’s nice to think about. It’s even nicer to stop thinking
about that, look at those numbers, and just feel dope as hell, if
only for a moment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perhaps two moments, though. A new number arrived the following day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;30:&lt;/strong&gt; After tweaking some things, the job ran in less than 30
minutes. That’s some astounding stuff.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 Aug 2013 22:40:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <link>http://www.arponr.com/numbers-at-google</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.arponr.com/numbers-at-google</guid>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
