<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>arponr</title>
    <description>blog by arpon</description>
    <link>http://www.arponr.com</link>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 12 Jun 2015 20:31:20 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://www.arponr.com/feed.xml" rel="self"/>
    
    <item>
      <title>Characters in global equivariant homotopy theory</title>
      <description>
</description>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Mar 2015 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <link>http://www.arponr.com</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.arponr.com/senior-thesis</guid>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Transcendence in Infinite Jest</title>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;introduction&quot;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One needs only reach the twelfth page of &lt;em&gt;Infinite Jest&lt;/em&gt; to be
confronted with philosophy: Hal’s very first utterances express his
beliefs that “the influence of Kierkegaard on Camus is
underestimated”, that “Hobbes is just Rousseau in a dark mirror”, and
“with Hegel, that transcendence is absorption”. It is my belief that
these statements are not simply supercilious name-dropping (either on
Hal’s or David Foster Wallace’s part), but serious hints that central
aspects of the novel should be understood in a philosophical
context. This essay works towards justifying this belief using (a few
of) the remaining 1067 pages of the text, specifically focusing on
this notion of &lt;em&gt;transcendence&lt;/em&gt; which Hal immediately refers to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The notion of transcendence takes on many forms throughout philosophy,
but I think two are most relevant to understanding its form in the
novel. First we have the transcendence of existential philosophy, in
particular of Jean Paul Sartre, which is the human’s freedom and
responsibility to actively relate to, rather than be passively
determined by, its &lt;em&gt;facticity&lt;/em&gt;, the physical, social, and historical
facts which constitute it as an object in the world. Second we have
transcendentalist philosophy, which stresses the power of the isolated
individual to transcend the conformity of society, and is in part
inspired by Immanuel Kant’s concept of the individual’s
“transcendental” a priori knowledge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In what follows I argue that we may understand &lt;em&gt;Infinite Jest&lt;/em&gt;’s
philosophy of transcendence through the concept’s existential and
transcendental manifestations, and then apply this understanding to
shed a bit of light on the mystery of two characters in the novel,
Lyle and Hal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;transcendence&quot;&gt;Transcendence&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To give grounds for the relevance of existential philosophy in the
novel it suffices to consider the story at its highest level (both
geographically and conceptually), namely in Marathe and Steeply’s
discussion on America. At the center of their discourse is “freedom!
… as if it were obvious to all people what it wants to mean, this
word. But look: it is not so simple as that. Your freedom is the
freedom-&lt;em&gt;from&lt;/em&gt; … But what of the freedom-&lt;em&gt;to&lt;/em&gt;? Not just
free-&lt;em&gt;from&lt;/em&gt;. … How for the person to freely choose?”
(320). Marathe’s questions here fit very nicely into the framework of
existentialism, articulating Sartre’s conception of transcendence,
that human freedom is a responsibility, condition, and limitation in
relating to the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can interpret Marathe’s “freedom-&lt;em&gt;from&lt;/em&gt;” the world as the simplest
form of transcending facticity, understanding one’s right to
choose. Then his “freedom-&lt;em&gt;to&lt;/em&gt;” act, what he suggests is the far more
critical and difficult aspect of freedom, can be interpreted as
actually applying this right to relate with the facticity of the
world. The novel depicts the result of only exercising the former,
easier end of freedom as an ironic loss of freedom: addiction, either
to drugs or the Entertainment. The viewers who become “stuck”,
“trapped in some sort of middle”, “lost” (647) in the Entertainment
forego their role as actors in the world, and hence are reduced to
objects in the world, their facticity. This intimates one of &lt;em&gt;Infinite
Jest&lt;/em&gt;’s many double-binds: one cannot hide from the facticity of the
world in transcending one’s facticity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the novel moreover suggests that solving this existential
double-bind of transcendence lies in another form of transcendence,
namely transcendence of the self. This is expressed most clearly by
Schtitt’s basically fascist philosophy of tennis:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Tennis’s beauty’s infinite roots are self-competitive. You compete
with your own limits to transcend the self in imagination and
execution. Disappear inside the game: break through limits:
transcend: improve: win. Which is why tennis is an essentially
tragic enterprise, to improve and grow as a serious junior, with
ambitions. You seek to vanquish and transcend the limited self whose
limits make the game possible in the first place. It is tragic and
sad and chaotic and lovely. All life is the same, as citizens of the
human State: the animating limits are within, to be killed and
mourned, over and over again. (84)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here transcendence is positioned as antithetical to
transcendentalism. The “limits” one must transcend do not come from
society but from “within” the self. This opposition to
transcendentalism is made explicit when Pemulis tries to convince Hal
to take DMZ by saying that the “stuff’s original intent was to induce
what they called quote transcendent experiences in get this chronic
alcoholics”, and Hal asks in clarification, “Was it transcendent? The
term in Struck’s literature? Or was it transcendental?” Pemulis shrugs
off the difference but his next choice of words is: “some low-risk
transcendentalism with me and the Human Hatchet could be…”
(1064). This suggests that the novel attributes the degenerative
spiral of addicted, “freedom-&lt;em&gt;from&lt;/em&gt;” behavior into static facticity to
a type of transcendentalist worship of the power and rights of the
individual. Schtitt’s transcendence is instead about “vanquish[ing]”
the boundaries of the individual, embracing the “freedom-&lt;em&gt;to&lt;/em&gt;” give
oneself up to “[s]omething bigger than the self”, as Marathe says
(107).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Schtitt’s mention of the infinite and emphasis on the self as a limit
indicate a crucial link between transcendence and infinity in the
text. One such link is in the grammatical sense of the word
&lt;em&gt;infinite&lt;/em&gt;—as in a verb form not limited by tense, person, or
number—which seems to reflect Schtitt’s notion of transcendence, of
partaking in something that is not restricted by some specific subject
or time, or that “outlives you” (107). Another link lies in Avril’s
proposal that: “There are, apparently, persons who are deeply afraid
of their own emotions, particularly the painful ones. Grief, regret,
sadness. Sadness especially, perhaps. Dolores describes these persons
as afraid of obliteration, emotional engulfment. As if something truly
and thoroughly felt would have no end or bottom. Would become infinite
and engulf them” (765). So perhaps Schtitt’s “human State” can be
interpreted as simply the human state, i.e. the emotion and sentiment
which connects one to others. This is reinforced by “Hal, who’s empty
but not dumb, theoriz[ing] privately that what passes for hip cynical
transcendence of sentiment is really some kind of fear of being really
human, since to be really human (at least as he conceptualizes it) is
probably to be unavoidably sentimental and naive and goo-prone and
generally pathetic, is to be in some basic interior way forever
infantile, some sort of not-quite-right-looking infant dragging itself
anaclitically around the map, with big wet eyes and froggy-soft skin,
huge skull, gooey drool” (694–695). This last description immediately
brings Mario to mind, which fits given Mario’s close relationship with
Schtitt, complete devotion to and love of his family, and that he is
“not exactly insensitive when it comes to people” (763).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The above evinces the following picture of transcendence in &lt;em&gt;Infinite
Jest&lt;/em&gt;: the self is a boundary between and limit of the infinity of
sentiment within and the infinity of the world without, and true
transcendence is the transcendence of this boundary, the ability to
interface honestly with the world. This transcendence involves both
recognizing the inner infinity—transcending one’s facticity as a
human being with attitudes and feelings—and the outer
infinity—turning one’s transcendence on the other facticities of the
world, connecting to the human s/State. This sits in contradistinction
to trascendentalism, which the novel depicts not as the erasure of
this boundary or transcendence of this limit, but as a false, ironic
rejection of the inner emotion and pure consumption (or ingestion) of
the outer world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;lyle&quot;&gt;Lyle&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While &lt;em&gt;Infinite Jest&lt;/em&gt;’s philosophy of transcendence is best verbally
expressed by Schtitt, I believe it is best embodied by Lyle, whose
mystery is apparent from his first description:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;An oiled guru sits in yogic full lotus in Spandex and tank top. He’s
maybe forty. He’s in full lotus on top of the towel dispenser just
above the shoulder-pull station in the weight room of the Enfield
Tennis Academy, Enfield MA. … Nobody knows where he comes from or
why he’s allowed to stay, but he’s always in there, sitting yogic
about a meter off the rubberized floor of the weight room. His tank
top says TRANSCEND in silkscreen; on the back it’s got DEUS
PROVIDEBIT in Day-Glo orange. … This guru lives off the sweat of
others. Literally. The fluids and salts and fatty acids. He’s like a
beloved nut. He’s an E.T.A. institution.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If his tank top is not enough of a visual hint at his embodiment of
transcendence, his being a yogic guru described as if floating in
lotus position above the ground must be; and if it isn’t, the fact
that he later literally “hovers cross-legged just a couple mm. above
the top of the towel dispenser in the unlit weight room, eyes rolled
up white” (700) undoubtedly is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But his transcendence runs far deeper than these images. His entire
role at E.T.A. is to connect with others: “Like all good listeners, he
has a way of attending that is at once intense and assuasive: the
supplicant feels both nakedly revealed and sheltered, somehow, from
all possible judgment. It’s like he’s working as hard as you. You both
of you, briefly, feel unalone” (388). This precisely describes his
ability to transcend the boundary between his self and his
“supplicant”. He lives for and off of (the sweat of) the other. And
most strikingly, he is not an individual, but an “institution”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In light of this I want to interpret a couple of perplexing details
about Lyle. The first is his advice to Ortho Stice: “Do not
underestimate objects! Lyle says he finds it impossible to overstress
this: do &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; underestimate objects” (394). This reflects the idea
that in transcending one’s facticity, one must not disregard facticity
all together; i.e. one must actively relate to the objects in the
world to avoid getting lost in the self. This then supports the idea
that the unexplained misplacement of objects in E.T.A., including
Stice’s bed, are an attempt by James Incandenza to draw Hal out of his
self, to have Hal actually open himself to the world and its
objects. The second is the fact that the back of Lyle’s “TRANSCEND”
tank top reads “DEUS PROVIDEBIT”, i.e. “GOD WILL PROVIDE”. This hints
at the significance of faith and worship in the novel’s conception of
transcendence. This is expressed by Marathe as well: “Our attachments
are our temple, what we worship, no? What we give ourselves to, what
we invest with faith.” Lyle’s position as an essentially religious
guru points at the idea that connection between one’s honest emotions
and the infinity of the human s/State outside the self relies on an
essentially religious faith in some sort of god.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;hal&quot;&gt;Hal&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally we turn to Hal. These days the term “existential angst” evokes
the image of a clichéd sullen teenager lying in bed in a dark room,
clichéd melancholy alternative rock drowning out clichéd parental
yelling through the door. Maybe Hal isn’t so extremely clichéd but
he’s still a teenager wrestling with the idea that “inside [him]
there’s pretty much nothing at all, he knows. His Moms Avril hears her
own echoes inside him and thinks what she hears is him, and this makes
Hal feel the one thing he feels to the limit, lately: he is lonely”
(694). While it would be easy to cynically cast aside this emptiness
and loneliness as teenage naivete, &lt;em&gt;Infinite Jest&lt;/em&gt; suggests that “the
cliché ‘I don’t know who I am’ unfortunately turns out to be more than
a cliché” (204), and should be considered in the light of the serious
philosophy from which existential angst originated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Indeed, I claim that Hal’s driving struggle in the novel is the
classic existential struggle of transcending one’s facticity. Hal
specifically faces the facticity of genetics and authority: as a
“lexical prodigy” he is simply an echo of his mother, and as
“late-blooming prodigy and possible genius at tennis” he is simply an
echo of his father. Rather than actively forming his identity he is
“being encouraged to identify himself” through these echoes, acting
apparently exclusively to make his mother and in fact “every
authority-figure in his world and beyond very proud indeed”
(155). Hal’s father (as the professional conversationalist) pleads
that Hal “recognize the occasional vista beyond your own generous
Mondragonoid nose’s fleshy tip” (31)—Mondragon being Avril’s maiden
name—indicating that Hal only sees his mother in front of him, or
perhaps only interacts with the world as filtered through his
mother. This lack of identity is what gives truth for Hal to “the fact
that that the great transcendent horror is loneliness, excluded
encagement in the self” (694); he perceives his self only as a cage of
facticity which he is unable to break free of, transcend.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is why the sudden shift from third- to first-person narration of
Hal (851) is so pivotal; and why it is so important in the opening
scene of the novel that Hal believes, “I am in here” (3); and why Hal
is desperate to communicate:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I am not just a boy who plays tennis. I have an intricate
history. Experiences and feelings. I’m complex. … it transcends
the mechanics. I’m not a machine. I feel and believe. … I’m not
just a creatus, manufactured, conditioned, bred for a
function. (11–12)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The mechanics and conditioning he “transcends” are precisely his
facticity. The tragedy then is that, though he now “feel[s] and
believe[s]” in his identity, he “cannot make himself understood” (10):
“I look out. Directed my way is horror. … ‘I am not what you see and
hear.’” (12–13). Given the analysis above, Hal’s inability to
communicate his feelings with others indicates that he has not truly
transcended. While Lyle is able to bridge the infinities within and
without him, transcend himself to become an “institution” with which
others honestly connect, Hal remains stuck in his finitude, unable to
connect.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the real (but not unsatisfying) sense for me in which
&lt;em&gt;Infinite Jest&lt;/em&gt; does not finish: we are left with an incompletely
transformed, untranscended Hal, one which reflects the deep loneliness
in the incredible difficulty of both recognizing the infinity within
the self and transcending the boundary (the self) between this
infinity and the infinities of others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;references&quot;&gt;References&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;David Foster Wallace, &lt;em&gt;Infinite Jest&lt;/em&gt;, Back Bay Books, 1996.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
      <pubDate>Fri, 21 Nov 2014 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <link>http://www.arponr.com/ij-transc</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.arponr.com/ij-transc</guid>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Vector fields and the J-homomorphism</title>
      <description>
</description>
      <pubDate>Fri, 09 May 2014 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <link>http://www.arponr.com</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.arponr.com/vfields</guid>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Defining the cotangent complex</title>
      <description>
</description>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Dec 2013 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <link>http://www.arponr.com</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.arponr.com/quillen-cotangent</guid>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Dold-Kan correspondence</title>
      <description>
</description>
      <pubDate>Sat, 26 Oct 2013 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <link>http://www.arponr.com</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.arponr.com/doldkan</guid>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Numbers at Google</title>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This is a post about some numbers that I saw at work one day during my
internship at Google. I present them to you without further ado.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;21:&lt;/strong&gt; I got to run a job with 21 terabytes of input. &lt;em&gt;Tera&lt;/em&gt;. And
that’s compressed.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;10000000000:&lt;/strong&gt; 21 TB means I got to compute statistics on data
sets of size greater than 10 billion. &lt;em&gt;Billion&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;3:&lt;/strong&gt; It took fewer than 3 hours to run that job. I love MapReduce
and resources.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;23:&lt;/strong&gt; Later on, after realising I had made some stupid mistakes, I
needed to run that job again (and because it felt so damn cool the
first time, and I could, so why not). Anyway it turns out the data
was on some machines on the East Coast, and the job was running on
machines on the West Coast. That’s efficiency. Well so I (and, by
“I”, I mean someone else on my team who actually knew what he was
doing) managed to get the job running next door to the data. And for
ten minutes or so, that 21 TB was being sent to the job at more than
23 gigbatyes per second. &lt;em&gt;Giga&lt;/em&gt;. Holy bandwidth, batman.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So it turns out working at Google indeed has perks. Those numbers are
all due to some really smart people that work (or have worked)
here. That’s nice to think about. It’s even nicer to stop thinking
about that, look at those numbers, and just feel dope as hell, if
only for a moment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perhaps two moments, though. A new number arrived the following day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;30:&lt;/strong&gt; After tweaking some things, the job ran in less than 30
minutes. That’s some astounding stuff.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 Aug 2013 22:40:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <link>http://www.arponr.com/numbers-at-google</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.arponr.com/numbers-at-google</guid>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
