<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>arponr</title>
    <description>blog by arpon</description>
    <link>http://www.arponr.com</link>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 16 Jun 2015 19:17:30 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://www.arponr.com/feed.xml" rel="self"/>
    
    <item>
      <title>Somewhere in Finland</title>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Today I woke up in Finland, somewhere, in the grass. To be fair, I did yesterday too, and the day before that, and … well, I guess I don’t really know what I mean by ‘today’, though, or ‘yesterday’ or ‘the day before that’ or …. What I mean is, for some time now I have been falling asleep and waking up in the grass, somewhere in Finland.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I arrived to the country in June on a sparse red-eye flight, JFK to HEL. Sitting in seat 21B between an empty 21A and 21C, I felt for the first time in more than twenty years of quasifrequent air travel the freedom to occupy as much space as I wanted to, or rather as god had always intended me to. The word ‘freedom’ is not deployed lightly here; the experience was truly a liberating one, for it revealed to me the following. All of the sensory irritants that accompany my conception of (economy/coach/third-class) air travel—the drone and odor of the cabin, the pilot’s meaningless announcements, the random dinging of the fasten-seatbelt sign, the clanging of carts filled with stimulants and depressants up and down the narrow aisles—these irritants are not actually irritating at all in and of themselves. While there is indeed an acrid bile stirred within me by the thought of an airliner, these inanimate and invisible environs are not its source. Their inanimacy and invisibility just make them easy and socially acceptable targets upon which I, the civilized citizen, have been trained to spew my bile. No, the source is nothing other than the restless shifting and insistent whispering and unabating, unadulterated existence of &lt;em&gt;people&lt;/em&gt; just millimeters in every direction of my heartrendingly compressed body.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So on this sparse red-eye, I—neighborless, uncompressed, liberated—fell gently asleep to the cabin’s reassuring whir and the pilot’s gibberish lullaby, the silent miming of the flight attendant tilting and blurring as I retreated beneath warm darkness behind eyelids. And, uninteruppted by others’ bodily functions, I slept soundly. I awoke during the plane’s final descent, burnt sunrise behind eyelids dissolving into faint light and refocusing outside the oval window. Crawling over to 21A and pulling myself up ever so slightly, I let my head rest at the edge of the oval cut-out and fixed my gaze on the rising sun. I made no additional voluntary movements for the remaining few minutes of the flight. It was the most conscientously I’ve ever watched a sunrise, and I think I waited for the right sunrise to do so. It rose so slowly and deliberately, so heavily. In those final minutes, I felt I understood a bit closer to my core the heaviness of the sun.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The items I brought with me to Finland can be divided into two categories. The first consists of those items covering my body (allowing me to move discreetly through society, like one of its own):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;a pair of pants, on the darker end of khaki;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;a pair of boxers underneath;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;a short-sleeved t-shirt, medium grey and undecorated;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;a long-sleeved button-up shirt, made of faded blue flannel;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;a jacket, darker blue and sort of rugged—or maybe that’s just how it made me feel;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;a pair of sneakers, bright red;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;a pair of socks underneath;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;an old black backpack.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second consists of those items contained in the aformentioned backpack:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;my passport&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;a collection of short stories by Franz Kafka;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;a black leather notebook;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;a mechanical pencil, along with extra lead and an eraser.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;an iPod nano (you know, one of those old-fashioned gadgets which, believe it or not, just outputs music) and a pair of headphones.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I left behind anything that could tell me the time, planning to leave
here at sunset, which should be sometime in August. Perhaps this
informs my confusion about all those words containing the word ‘day’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wasn’t hungry when I woke up today. To be fair, I wasn’t yesterday either, or the day before that . . . and that same spiel about today and yesterday and time and the sun of the Finnish summer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I just lay in the grass, letting myself wake up, one bone at a time. The grass here is lush, green, soft, warm, beautiful, and so on. It’s grass that you can lie in, where you can bathe in the tireless summer sun, float down into a dreamless sleep and drift somewhere, some place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Some place empty, but not cold or dark for even here the sun has not set—does time even pass? You are fixed here, and unsure if that or anything else will ever change, so you wait, the sun overhead, and you wait, and finally the sun has poured into you all that it could and you wake up, in Finland, somewhere, slowly, one bone at a time.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And in those final minutes, which may very well have been hours, I felt the heavy sun of the Finnish summer sink into me, slowly and deliberately. I dissolve into faint light, one bone at a time.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Jun 2015 19:17:30 -0400</pubDate>
      <link>http://www.arponr.com/finland</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.arponr.com/finland</guid>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Heart Hotel</title>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Waft up into the atmosphere with all the other in-flight scents, for
some precisely prescribed but immaterial length of time, drifting and
swirling and who knows what goes on at those altitudes, till the
prescription runs out and you are sucked down into the world. Fall
through infinity—fractals of branching passages, vague semiotics,
and cordoned sinusoids—till infinity spits you out in front of
Arrivals. Watch sinister, swarthy creatures slouching by towards
Departures while you wait to diffuse into some vehicle which barely
stops and then flows, onward, submerged in a viscous
cavalcade. Surface and emerge, finally, at your destination. The night
is dark red and pulsing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Come inside, welcome. This hotel is nestled at the heart of me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;floor-eleven&quot;&gt;Floor Eleven&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s October of 2004, and the hallway is lined with those lurid
lockers, the ones which send the average American hurtling back in
fits of nostalgia toward some teenage point in spacetime. Only this is
one of my not-even-teen years, and it’s right here and now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Look at me—no, not at me, at not-even-teen me—leaning like I must
have seen on tv against an orange locker adjacent to her orange
locker. I’m fidgeting, imperceptibly I hope, maybe even just
inwardly. A pen full of red ink comes out of my pocket and into my
hand and begins to fidget with me. What am I saying?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“. . . .”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I capital-L Like, a.k.a. like-like, her. Who knows why. Are we even
friends? Seriously, what am I saying? That capital-L has planted
itself right inside me, its roots reach far deeper than my sorry logic
could ever dig.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“. . . .”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My neck squirms, eyes wander, searching for some wit or charm or
something, but something else finds me: the pen explodes. The
idiomatic explosion is more metaphoric than literal though, the spray
of ink scrawny and pathetic, yet in perfectly catastrophic trajectory,
existing in all the wrong places and moments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am too young for innuendo to apply. This is real.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dear god, I am bleeding all over her and her baby-blue North Face
fleece. So many dreams shatter around me as my glossy oxygenated red
struggles to harmonize with her soft baby-blue, like some grotesque
hall of inconsistently colored mirrors. My neck snaps into place, eyes
freeze, and, as neck- and eye-mobility appear to be gradually
transferred over to her, she slowly lifts her heavy gaze from her
orange locker. The gaze, expressing and therefore evoking terror,
thuds down onto me. I need to react. I Like her so much I’m
bleeding. I need a reaction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I laugh. I double over, laughing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Her terror metamorphoses in between eye-blinks: into anger, then
sadness, then disgust; all those feelings I decide between mirroring
eye-blinks I had always wanted from her. Yes, of course, I hate her
with all my heart.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“. . . .”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Does she say something? A ventricle is pounding at my ear, and I am
far too busy with my laughter. A bell interposes to notify us the day
is over, cackling along with me as my brand new nemesis storms off
into the afternoon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;me: hey s—-
s: hi what’s up?
me: not much, chilling
…
s: you want to see this video my dance team recorded?
me: yeak ok
s: [url]
…
me: i didn’t really like it
s: … are you serious
me: i guess i didn’t really get it
s: what
s: i’m dancing what’s there to get
me: sorry
s: why would you say that
me: sorry!
me: it’s not about you i guess i just don’t get dance
s: so still
s: why would you say you don’t like it
s: k—- said he liked it
s: why couldn’t you just
me: sorry&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

</description>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Jun 2015 15:47:23 -0400</pubDate>
      <link>http://www.arponr.com/hotel</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.arponr.com/hotel</guid>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Logic</title>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;There’s a dream I often have (I’ve had it about three times a week for
the last twenty years). There are two humans, one male and one female,
standing in a forest. I know that the forest is in upstate New York
(U.S.A.), though I can unfortunately be no more specific than that,
and really it’s not even clear to me how I know that the forest is
where I say it is. The man is leaning against one of the hundreds of
trees surrounding them; he is playing a worn acoustic guitar and is
singing. The woman is roughly two paces away, facing the man, and is
singing too. From the position and movement of the sun I’ve deduced
that it’s around 4:30pm and that the slight breeze is entering the
scene from the northeast. The humans play a single song: this is the
dream.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I suppose this puts me in better position than the countless children
paralyzed by recurring nightmares, or the countless parents therefore
suffering from parades of sleepless nights. But, of course, such
comparisons are arbitrary and meaningless. There are millions and
millions of dimensions along which I might compare myself and little
nightmare-plagued Billy, and how could I ever decide on the relative
values of all of these dimensions? In one dimension I am listening to
quiet folk music in the midst of a forest while Billy escapes the
grasp of a vegetable-shaped monster. In another, Billy wakes up to a
mother’s soft lullaby while I drift from one inky nothingness into
another into another.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Two humans stand in the autumn of a New York forest. Radically old
wood towers around them; equally old wood lies hollowed, carved, and
stringed in the arms of one. The wood and the strings and the humans
vibrate. Listen: the vibrations are in New York and in your bedroom
and ripple out from your heart and for two moments you feel the beauty
of evolution, history, time, entropy, everything which created a
species that stands in melody and harmony among shimmering sunlight
and dancing leaves. And forget the two subsequent moments of cynicism,
for it is not actually True that the bacteria and the insects have as
much claim to the Earth as you. The Earth pulses with the beat of your
music. And forget the two subsubsequent moments during which you
realize that maybe the insects think they are making music too because
what is music and maybe we are just insects and…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Do not deduce yourself out of the Truth. Remember beauty and
vibrations and your heart. Remember.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Jun 2015 15:47:04 -0400</pubDate>
      <link>http://www.arponr.com/logic</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.arponr.com/logic</guid>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Wind-Up Bird Chronicle</title>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;ideas&quot;&gt;Ideas&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The wind-up bird
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;forgot to track this for the first ~200 pages&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The vacant house
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;43–44, 46, 172, 2384&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The flow, water, wells
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;51, 55, 58–59, 105, 125, 162, 175, 179, 213, 224–225&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Light destructive / blinding
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;130, 158–159, 163, 165–167, 170, 208–209, 220, 222&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;quotations&quot;&gt;Quotations&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;But after all, Mr. Okada, when one is speaking of the essence of things, it often happens that one can only speak in generalities. Concrete things certainly do command attention, but they are often little more than trivia. Side trips. The more one tries to see into the distance, the more generalized things become. (44)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The point is, not to resist the flow. You go up when you’re supposed to go up and down when you’re supposed to go down. When you’re supposed to go up, find the highest tower and climb to the top. When you’re supposed to go down, find the deepest well and go down to the bottom. When there’s no flow, stay still. If you resist the flow, everything dries up, the world is darkness. (51)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;On days like this the clouds probably absorbed the sounds from the surface of the earth. And not just sounds. All kinds of things. Perceptions, for example. (58)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It was a narrow world, a world that was standing still. But the narrower it became, and the more it betook of stillness, the more this world that enveloped me seemed to overflow with things and people that could only be called strange. They had been there all the while, it seemed, waiting in the shadows for me to stop moving. And every time the wind-up bird came to my yard to wind its spring, the world descended more deeply into chaos. (125)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It seemed to take a very long time for me to hit bottom. In reality, it could not have been more than a few seconds, but I do recall thinking about a great many things on my way down. I thought about my hometown, so far away. I thought about the girl I slept with just once before they shipped me out. I thought about my parents. I recall feeling grateful that I had a younger sister and not a brother: even if I was killed, they would still have her and not have to worry about her being taken by the army. I thought about rice cakes wrapped in oak leaves. Then I slammed into dry ground and lost consciousness for a moment. It felt as if all the air inside me had burst through the walls of my body. I thudded against the well bottom like a sandbag. (163)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I had that tendency toward solitude common to only children. When trying to acomplish something serious, I liked to do it myself. Having to check things out with other people and get them understand seemed to me a great waste of time and energy when it was a lot easier to work alone in silence.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Jun 2015 15:46:36 -0400</pubDate>
      <link>http://www.arponr.com/windup</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.arponr.com/windup</guid>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Structures on manifolds</title>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I’m trying to learn some stable homotopy theory this summer, and am
starting out by reading about bordism. My first goal is to understand
Thom’s computation of the unoriented bordism ring, i.e., the
classification of unoriented compact smooth manifolds up to
bordism. I’ve been following a couple of sets of notes by &lt;a href=&quot;//www-math.mit.edu/~hrm/papers/cobordism.pdf&quot;&gt;Haynes
Miller&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;//www.math.umass.edu/~weston/oldpapers/cobord.pdf&quot;&gt;Tom Weston&lt;/a&gt;. I’m hoping to keep my own
detailed notes along the way, which I’ll probably put up at the end of
the summer. But I’ll try to post about some of it here as I go, too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This post is the result of me getting rather confused about the
various bordism problems about “strucured” manifolds, and is
essentially just an attempt to sort out how I should think about these
“structures”. The structure comes from the stable normal bundle, so we
begin there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;\begin{notation}
Let $TM$ denote the tangent bundle of a smooth manifold $M$.
\end{notation}&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;\begin{definition}{normal-bundle}
Let $i \c M \to N$ be an immersion of smooth manifolds. The &lt;em&gt;normal
bundle&lt;/em&gt; $\nu_i$ of $i$ (or of $M$ in $N$) is the vector bundle on $M$
defined by the short exact sequence $0 \to TM \to i^*TN \to \nu_i \to
0$.
\end{definition}&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;\begin{proposition}{normal-composition}
Let $i \c L \to M$ and $j \c M \to N$ be immersions of smooth
manifolds. Let $k \ce j \circ i$. Then there is a short exact sequence
[
0 \to \nu_i \to \nu_k \to i^*\nu_j \to 0
]
of bundles on $L$.
\end{proposition}&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;\begin{proof}
Since pullback of vector bundles is exact we have
[
i^&lt;em&gt;\nu_j \iso i^&lt;/em&gt;\l(\f{j^&lt;em&gt;TN}{TM}\r) \iso \f{k^&lt;/em&gt;TN}{i^&lt;em&gt;TM} \iso
\f{k^&lt;/em&gt;TN/TL}{i^*TM/TL} \iso \f{\nu_k}{\nu_i}.
]
\end{proof}&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;\begin{definition}{stable-normal}
Let $M$ be a compact smooth manifold. Let $[\xi] \in [M, BO]$ be the
homotopy class classifying the tangent bundle $TM \to M$ (stably). The
&lt;em&gt;stable normal bundle&lt;/em&gt; $\nu_M$ of $M$ is defined as the inverse of
$[\xi]$ in the group $[M, BO] \iso \wt{KO}(M)$.
\end{definition}&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;\begin{remark}{normal-classifies-stable}
Note if $i \c M \to \R^n$ is an immersion (which always exists!) then
by definition we have a short exact sequence
[
0 \to TM \to i^*T\R^n \to \nu_i \to 0.
]
Since $T\R^n$ is trivial it follows that $\nu_i$ is inverse to $TM$ in
$\wt{KO}(M)$. Thus the stable classifying map $M \to BO$ of $\nu_i$
determines the homotopy class of the stable normal bundle $\nu_M$
(hence the terminology). But note that, by definition, $\nu_M$ does
not depend on the choice of dimension $n$ and immersion $i$.
\end{remark}&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;\begin{notation}
Suppose we have maps $a,b,c \c X \to Y$. We denote a homotopy $h \c X
\times I \to Y$ from $a$ to $b$ by by $h \c a \to b$. We denote the
composition of homotopies $h \c a \to b$ and $k \c b \to c$ by $k *
h$.
\end{notation}&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;\begin{definitions}{f-structure-prelim}
Let $f \c B \to BO$ be any map and $g \c M \to BO$ a map from a
compact smooth manifold $M$. An &lt;em&gt;$f$-structure&lt;/em&gt; on $g$ is an
equivalence class of homotopy lifts $(\bar g, h)$ of $g$, where&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;a &lt;em&gt;homotopy lift&lt;/em&gt; of $g$ is a map $\bar g \c M \to B$ and a homotopy
$h \c f \circ \bar g \to g$;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;two pairs $(\bar g_1, h_1)$ and $(\bar g_2, h_2)$ are equivalent if
and only if there is a homotopy $\bar h \c \bar g_1 \to \bar g_2$
such that $h_2 * (f \circ \bar h) = h_1$.
\end{definitions}&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;\begin{lemma}{f-structure-bijection}
Let $f \c B \to BO$ and $g \c M \to BO$ as in
\ref{f-structure-prelim}. Then:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;a homotopy $k \c g \to g’$ determines a bijection $\theta_k$
between the $f$-structures on $g$ and $g’$;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;if $k’ \c g’ \to g’’$ is another homotopy, then the bijections
determined by $k$, $k’$, and $k’’ \ce k’ * k$ commute:
[
\begin{xy}
\xymatrix {
  {f\text{-structures on }g} \ar@{&amp;lt;-&amp;gt;}[r]&lt;em&gt;{\theta_k}
  \ar@{&amp;lt;-&amp;gt;}[dr]&lt;/em&gt;{\theta&lt;em&gt;{k’’}} &amp;amp;
  {f\text{-structures on }g’} \ar@{&amp;lt;-&amp;gt;}[d]&lt;/em&gt;{\theta_{k’}} &lt;br /&gt;
  &amp;amp; {f\text{-structures on }g’’}.
}
\end{xy}
]
\end{lemma}&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;\begin{proof}
It suffices to simply give any maps $\theta_k$ satisfying (ii), since
then bijectivity is immediate from taking inverse homotopies. Let $k
\c g \to g’$ be a homotopy. There is a map from homotopy lifts of $g$
to homotopy lifts of $g’$ via $(\bar g, h) \mapsto (\bar g, k *
h)$. This evidently respects the equivalence relation so this descends
to give the map $\theta_k$. Property (ii) then clearly holds.
\end{proof}&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;\begin{definitions}{f-structure}
Let $f \c B \to BO$ be a map and $\xi \in [M, BO]$ a stable vector
bundle on a compact smooth manifold $M$. An &lt;em&gt;$f$-structure&lt;/em&gt; on $\xi$
is an equivalence class of pairs $(g,\sigma)$, where&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;$g$ is a map $M \to BO$ classifying $\xi$, i.e. $[g] = \xi$, and
$\sigma$ is an $f$-structure on $g$;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;two pairs $(g,\sigma)$ and $(g’,\sigma’)$ are equivalent if and only
if there is a homotopy $k \c g \to g’$ such that $\sigma’ =
\theta_k(\sigma)$; here $\theta_k$ is as defined by
\ref{f-structure-bijection}, which also shows that this is in fact
an equivalence relation.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An &lt;em&gt;$f$-structure&lt;/em&gt; on $M$ is an $f$-structure on its stable normal
bundle $\nu_M$.
\end{definitions}&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;\begin{remarks}{f-structure-reform}
Note, since the $\theta_k$ are bijections, \ref{f-structure} is
equivalent to saying that an $f$-structure on $\xi$ is an
$f$-structure on $g$ for any fixed $g \c M \to BO$ clasifying $\xi$.
In the case that $f$ is a fibration we may reformulate this
further. Fix a $g \c M \to BO$ classifying $\xi$.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let $\sigma$ be an $f$-structure on $g$ determined by a homotopy lift
$(\bar g, h)$. The homotopy $h \c f \circ \bar g \to g$ can be lifted,
since $f$ is a fibration, to a homotopy $\bar h \c \bar g \to \bar g’$
so that we have equality $f \circ \bar g’ = g$ on the nose. By
\ref{f-structure-prelim}, $\bar h$ gives an equivalence between the
homotopy lifts $(\bar g, h)$ and $(\bar g’, \id_g)$, where $\id_g$ is
the constant homotopy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So any $f$-structure $\sigma$ has a representative $(\bar g, h)$
where $h = \id_g$. Observe that two lifts $(\bar g_1, \id_g)$ and
$(\bar g_2, \id_g)$ are equivalent if and only if there is a homotopy
$\bar h \c \bar g_1 \to \bar g_2$ such that $f \circ \bar h =
\id_g$, which precisely says that $\bar h$ is a &lt;em&gt;fibrewise
homotopy&lt;/em&gt;. So finally, we may say (when $f$ is a fibration) that an
$f$-structure on $\xi$ is a fibrewise homotopy class of
lifts $\bar g$ in the diagram
\begin{equation}{f-structure-lift}
\begin{xy}
\xymatrix {
  &amp;amp; B \ar[d]_{f} &lt;br /&gt;
  M \ar@{–&amp;gt;}[ur]^{\bar g} \ar[r]^g &amp;amp; BO;
}
\end{xy}
\end{equation}
remember that here $g$ is any fixed map $M \to BO$ classifying $\xi$,
and these lifts are on the nose, not up to homotopy.
\end{remarks}&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;\begin{examples}{f-examples}
Why should we care about fibrations $B \to BO$? Well, maybe the
primary class of examples will answer that. Whenever we have a
morphism of topological groups $\phi \c G \to O$ we get a fibration $f
\ce B\phi \c BG \to BO$. In particular if we have a sequence of
morphisms
[
\begin{xy}
\xymatrix {
  G(0) \ar[r] \ar[d] &amp;amp; G(1) \ar[r] \ar[d] &amp;amp; G(2) \ar[r] \ar[d] &amp;amp;
  \cdots \ar[d] &lt;br /&gt;
  O(0) \ar[r] &amp;amp; O(1) \ar[r] &amp;amp; O(2) \ar[r] &amp;amp; \cdots
}
\end{xy}
]
we get a morphism $\colim_n G(n) \ec G \to O \ce \colim_n O(n)$.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, let’ consider \ref{f-structure} in the situation of a map $f \c
BG \to BO$. What is a homotopy lift $(\bar g, h)$ of a map $g \c M \to
BO$? Well $\bar g \c M \to BG$ classifies a principal $G$-bundle, and
the homotopy $h \c f \circ \bar g \to g$ specifies a reduction to $G$
of the structure group of the stable bundle $\xi$ classified by
$g$. And two homotopy lifts are equivalent when they induce isomorphic
reductions to $G$. Thus, for this class of examples, an $f$-structure
on a stable bundle $\xi$ is precisely an isomorphism class of
reductions of $\xi$ to a $G$-bundle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So in this situation we will abusively refer to $f$-structures (on
bundles and manifolds) as &lt;em&gt;$G$-structures&lt;/em&gt;. Here are some important
subexamples:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The most basic case comes from the identity $\id \c O \to O$,
inducing $f = \id \c BO \to BO$. It is immediate from the
reformulated definition of $f$-structures in
\ref{f-structure-reform} that very vector bundle on a compact
smooth manifold, and hence every compact smooth manifold, has a
unique $O$-structure. (And of course you’d expect there to be a
unique reduction of structure group from $O$ to $O$.)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Slightly less trivially we have the inclusion $SO \to O$ coming
from the inclusions $SO(n) \to O(n)$. This induces the two-to-one
cover $BSO \to BO$ arising from a choice of orientation. Indeed an
$SO$-structure on a manifold is precisely an orientation. Given the
discussion above, this should be believable, since giving an
orientation on a $k$-dimensional is equivalent to giving a
reduction of structure group to $SO(k)$. But we’re working stably
so there are some more details to this. We’ll work through these
details below since for me this example provides the most
intuition.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The inclusions $U(n) \to O(2n)$ give a morphism $U \to O$ and hence
a fibration $BU \to BO$. A $U$-structure on a manifold is called an
&lt;em&gt;almost-complex structure&lt;/em&gt;. This gives rise to the setting of
complex bordism, which is supposed to be extremely important;
hopefully I will be posting about that later on this summer.
\end{examples}&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the remainder let $M$ denote a compact smooth manifold and $f \c
BSO \to BO$ the map discussed in \ref{f-examples}. We’ll finish the
post by proving that $SO$-structures and orientations on $M$ are the
same thing, as promised above.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;\begin{lemma}{normal-orient}
Let $i \c M \to \R^n$ be an immersion. Then giving an orientation on
$M$ is equivalent to giving an orientation on the normal bundle
$\nu_i$.
\end{lemma}&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;\begin{proof}
By \ref{normal-bundle} of $\nu_i$ we have an exact sequence $0 \to TM
\to i^*T\R^n \to \nu_i \to 0$. There is a canonical trivialisation and
orientation of $T\R^n$, so orienting $\nu_i$ is equivalent to
orienting $TM$. But it is well known that giving an orientation on $M$
is equivalent to giving an orientation on $TM$, so then we’re done.
\end{proof}&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;\begin{proposition}{SO-orientation}
Giving an $SO$-structure on $M$ is equivalent to giving an orientation
on $M$.
\end{proposition}&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;\begin{proof}
Fix an immersion $i \c M \to \R^n$. Let $p \ce \dim(\nu_i)$ Let $g_0
\c M \to BO(p)$ be a map classifying $\nu_i$ and let $g$ be the
composition $M \to BO(p) \to BO$. Recall from
\ref{normal-classifies-stable} that $[g] = \nu_M$, and hence by
\ref{f-structure-reform} that giving an $SO$-structure on $M$ is
equivalent to giving an $SO$-structure on $g$. Combining this with
\ref{normal-orient}, we just left to show that giving an
$SO$-structure on $g$ is equivalent to giving an orientation on
$\nu_i$.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;($\Rightarrow$) Suppose we have an $SO$-structure $\sigma$ on $g$,
represented by a homotopy lift $(\bar g, h)$. Since $M$ is compact,
and hence $M \times I$ is compact too, there must be some finite $q
\in \N$ such that the map $\bar g \c M \to BSO$ factors through
$BSO(q)$ and the homotopy $h \c f \circ \bar g \to g$ factors through
$BO(q)$. In particular we have that the factoring $g \c M \to BO(q)$
classifies the vector bundle $\nu_i \oplus \uR^{q-p}$, where $\uR$
denotes the one-dimensional trivial bundle. Now the map $M \to BSO(q)$
classifies an oriented vector bundle $\mu$ and the homotopy $h$ gives
an isomorphism of unoriented vector bundles $\mu \iso \nu_i \oplus
\uR^{q-p}$. With this isomorphism, the orientation on $\mu$ determines
an orientation on $\nu_i \oplus \uR^{q-p}$, and since $\uR^{q-p}$ is
canonically oriented this specifies an orientation on $\nu_i$.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We need to check this does not depend on the representative $(\bar g,
h)$. Note that taking $q$ larger in the previous paragraph does not
affect the resulting orientation on $\nu_i$ since the map $BSO(q) \to
BSO(q+1)$ by definition classifies $\xi \mapsto \xi \oplus \uR$ with
$\uR$ given its canonical orientation. Thus, given another
representing pair $(\bar g’, h’)$ of $\sigma$ we may also assume $\bar
g’$ factors through $BSO(q)$ and $h$ factors through $BO(q)$. Since
$(\bar g, h)$ and $(\bar g’, h’)$ are equivalent homotopy lifts we by
definition have a homotopy $\bar h \c \bar g \to \bar g’$ such that
$h’ * (f \circ \bar h) = h$. I.e., if $\bar g’ \c M \to BSO(q)$
classifies the oriented bundle $\mu’$, then we have specified an
isomorphism $\mu \iso \mu’$ of oriented vector bundles which commutes
with the (unoriented) isomorphisms $\mu \iso \nu_i \oplus \uR^{q-p}$
and $\mu’ \iso \nu_i \oplus \uR^{q-p}$. It follows that the induced
orientations on $\nu_i$ will agree.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;($\Leftarrow$) Suppose we have an orientation on $\nu_i$. This is
equivalent to specifying a reduction of structure group of $\nu_i$ to
$SO(p)$, that is, an oriented $p$-dimensional vector bundle $\mu$ and
an isomorphism of unoriented bundles $\alpha \c \mu \iso \nu_i$. Of
course this is equivalent to a map $\bar g_0 \c M \to BSO(p)$ and a
homotopy $h_0 \c f \circ \bar g_0 \to g_0$. By composing with the maps
$BSO(p) \to BSO$ and $BO(p) \to BO$ we get a homotopy lift $(\bar g,
h)$ of $g$ defining an $SO$-structure on $g$.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We need to check this does not depend on the choice of $\mu$ and
$\alpha$. Clearly another oriented bundle $\mu’$ and isomorphism
$\alpha’ \c \mu’ \iso \nu_i$ induces the same orientation on $\nu_i$
if and only if there is an isomorphism $\beta \c \mu \iso \mu’$ of
oriented bundles such that $\alpha’ \circ \beta = \alpha$. If $\mu’$
and $\alpha’$ correspond to a map $\bar g_0’ \c M \to BSO(p)$ and
homotopy $h_0’ \c f \circ \bar g_0’ \to g_0$ this is equivalent to
asking for a homotopy $\bar h \c \bar g_0 \to \bar g_0’$ such that
$h_0’ * (f \circ \bar h) = h_0$. Again composing with $BSO(p) \to BSO$
and $BO(p) \to BO$, this precisely determines an equivalence of the
homotopy lifts $(\bar g, h)$ and $(\bar g’, h’)$. Hence the resulting
$SO$-structure is well-defined.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The two constructions are evidently mutually inverse, so we win.
\end{proof}&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;\begin{remark}
Hopefully the argument in \ref{SO-orientation} has made it more clear
why we always need to specify our homotopy $f \circ \bar g \to g$, and
why the notion of equivalence of homotopy lifts is as it is in
\ref{f-structure-prelim}. In particular, observe that the commuting
condition on homotopies in the equivalence of homotopy lifts is
absolutely key. For example, suppose $\eta$ is an orientable bundle
and $\xi \iso \eta$ an isomorphism of unoriented bundles. The two
orientations on $\eta$ might in fact give isomorphic oriented bundles,
but tautologically won’t induce the same orientation on $\xi$ via the
isomorphism $\xi \iso \eta$. In this case the necessary commuting
condition isn’t satisfied. (Note, the two orientations on any
orientable bundle are always &lt;em&gt;stably&lt;/em&gt; isomorphic, since multiplication
by $-1$ on $\uR$ gives an orientation reversing isomorphism $\eta
\oplus \uR \iso \eta \oplus \uR$.)
\end{remark}&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Jun 2015 20:31:35 -0400</pubDate>
      <link>http://www.arponr.com/structures-on-manifolds</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.arponr.com/structures-on-manifolds</guid>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Bundles II: comparisons</title>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This is a continuation of the &lt;a href=&quot;/bundles-i-definitions&quot;&gt;previous post&lt;/a&gt;, in which we
defined a sheaf-theoretic notion of &lt;em&gt;bundle&lt;/em&gt; over a
space, in analogy with the notion of fibre bundles. This time we
deal with a couple of comparison problems. Namely, we discuss:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;why our notion of bundle is in fact a strict generalisation of the
notion of fibre bundle;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the “change of fibre”, or “associated bundle”, construction.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We start by defining the categories which will feature in our
comparisons. We fix a space $X$ as we did last time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;\begin{definitions}{fibre-bundle-cat}
Let $G$ be a topological group and $F$ a left
$G$-space. &lt;a href=&quot;/bundles-i-definitions/#bundles-structure-groups&quot;&gt;Recall&lt;/a&gt; that a $G$-bundle on $X$ with fibre
$F$ is a fibre bundle $\pi \c E \to X$ with fibre $F$ equipped with a
trivialisation ${(U_i,\kappa_i)}$ with transition maps in $G$. We
define a &lt;em&gt;morphism of $G$-bundles with fibre $F$&lt;/em&gt; to be a continous
map $\lambda \c E \to E’$ over $X$ and a common refinement ${V_j}$ of
${U_i}$ and ${U’&lt;em&gt;{i’}}$ satisfying the following condition. For
any $i,i’,j$ such that $V_j \subseteq U_i$ and $V_j \subseteq
U’&lt;/em&gt;{i’}$, the map
[
\begin{xy}
  \xymatrix{
    V_j \times F \ar[r]^{\kappa_i^{-1}} &amp;amp;
    \pi^{-1}(V_j) \ar[r]^{\lambda} &amp;amp;
    \pi’^{-1}(V_j) \ar[r]^{\kappa’_{i’}} &amp;amp;
    V_j \times F
  }
\end{xy}
]
is an automorphism of the form $(v,f) \mapsto (v, g(v)f)$, where $g$
is a map $V_j \to G$.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This defines the &lt;em&gt;category $\Bun_G(X;F)$ of $G$-bundles on
$X$ with fibre $F$&lt;/em&gt;.
\end{definitions}&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;\begin{definitions}{bundle-sheaf-cat}
Let $\G$ be a sheaf of groups on $X$ and $\F$ a left
$\G$-sheaf. &lt;a href=&quot;/bundles-i-definitions/#bundle-sheaf&quot;&gt;Recall&lt;/a&gt; that a $\G$-bundle on $X$ with
fibre $\F$ is a bundle $\E$ on $X$ with fibre $\F$ equipped with a
trivialisation ${(U_i,\kappa_i)}$ with transition morphisms in
$\G$. We define a &lt;em&gt;morphism of $\G$-bundles with fibre $\F$&lt;/em&gt; to be a
morphism $\lambda \c \E \to \E’$ of sheaves on $X$ and a common
refinement ${V_j}$ of ${U_i}$ and ${U’&lt;em&gt;{i’}}$ satisfying the
following condition. For any $i,i’,j$ such that $V_j \subseteq U_i$
and $V_j \subseteq U’&lt;/em&gt;{i’}$, the map
[
\begin{xy}
  \xymatrix{
    \F|&lt;em&gt;{V_j} \ar[r]^{\kappa_i^{-1}} &amp;amp;
    \E|&lt;/em&gt;{V_j} \ar[r]^{\lambda} &amp;amp;
    \E’|&lt;em&gt;{V_j} \ar[r]^{\kappa’&lt;/em&gt;{i’}} &amp;amp;
    \F|_{V_j}
  }
\end{xy}
]
is an automorphism given by the action of an element of $\G(V_j)$.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This defines the &lt;em&gt;category $\Bun_\G(X;\F)$ of $\G$-bundles on
$X$ with fibre $\F$&lt;/em&gt;.
\end{definitions}&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;\begin{remark}
Note that all morphisms of $G$-bundles with fibre $F$ and morphisms of
$\G$-bundles with fibre $\F$ are isomorphisms (i.e. $\Bun_G(X;F)$ and
$\Bun_\G(X;\F)$ are groupoids). These are the notions of isomorphism
we will use for these objects.
\end{remark}&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;\begin{remark}
It follows from a &lt;a href=&quot;/bundles-i-definitions/#auto-left&quot;&gt;lemma&lt;/a&gt; from last time that if $\lambda \c
\E \to \E’$ is a morphism of sheaves on $X$ with $\E,\E’$ both
principal $\G$-bundles (i.e. $\G$-torsors) then $\lambda$ is a morphism
in $\Bun_\G(X;\G)$ if and only if $\lambda$ is a morphism of right
$\G$-sheaves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After proving a similar (also easy) lemma for principal $G$-bundles,
we can also see that a continuous map $\lambda \c E \to E’$ over $X$
between principal $G$-bundles $E \to X$ and $E’ \to X$ is a morphism
in $\Bun_G(X;G)$ if and only if it is $G$-equivariant.
\end{remark}&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We now show that the topological $\Bun_G(X;F)$ is really a special
case of the sheaf-theoretic $\Bun_\G(X;\F)$. &lt;a href=&quot;/bundles-i-definitions/#map-sheaf&quot;&gt;Recall&lt;/a&gt; that
to a space $Y$ we may associate the sheaf $\u{Y}$ on $X$ of continuous
maps to $Y$.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;\begin{proposition}
Let $G$ be a topological group and $F$ a left $G$-space. Taking
sheaves of sections defines an equivalence of categories
[
\Bun_G(X;F) \iso \Bun_{\u{G}}(X;\u{F}).
]
\end{proposition}&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;\begin{proof}
Before beginning observe that the action of $G$ on $F$ certainly
defines an action of $\u{G}$ on $\u{F}$, so the right-hand category is
indeed defined.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, we first show that sheaves of sections in fact defines a functor
$\Bun_G(X;F) \to \Bun&lt;em&gt;{\u{G}}(X;\u{F})$. Let $\pi \c E \to X$ be a
$G$-bundle with fibre $F$ and trivialisation ${(U_i,\kappa_i)}$. Let
$\E$ denote the sheaf of sections of $\pi$. A section of $U \times F
\to U$ is simply a continuous map $U \to F$, so composition with the
homeomorphisms $\kappa_i \c \pi^{-1}(U_i) \to U_i \times F$ over $U_i$
determine isomorphisms $\u{\kappa}_i \c \E|&lt;/em&gt;{U_i} \to
\u{F}|&lt;em&gt;{U_i}$. Then the resulting transition morphism $\u{t}&lt;/em&gt;{ij} \ce
\u{\kappa}&lt;em&gt;i\u{\kappa}_j^{-1}$ is composition with the transition map
$\kappa_i\kappa_j^{-1}$, which is of the form
[
(U_i \cap U_j) \times F \to (U_i \cap U_j) \times F, \quad
(u,f) \mapsto (u, t&lt;/em&gt;{ij}(u)f)
]
for some map $t&lt;em&gt;{ij} \c U_i \cap U_j \to G$ since $\pi$ has structure
group $G$. Thus $\u{t}&lt;/em&gt;{ij}$ is given by the action of $t_{ij} \in
\u{G}(U_i \cap U_j)$. So indeed $\E$ equipped with the trivialisation
${(U_i, \u{\kappa}_i)}$ is a $\u{G}$-bundle with fibre $\u{F}$.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This defines the functor on objects. For morphisms, a map $\lambda \c
E \to E’$ over $X$ defines (again via composition) a morphism of
sheaves $\u{\lambda} \c \E \to \E’$. That the common refinement and
condition defining a morphism in $\Bun_G(X;F)$ imply the condition
defining a morphism in $\Bun_{\u{G}}(X;\u{F})$ is the same as the
argument above showing that $\E$ has structure group $\u{G}$ if $\pi$
has structure group $G$.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We now sketch why this actually gives an equivalence:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Essential surjectivity: Suppose we have a $\u{G}$-bundle $\E$ with
fibre $\F$ and trivialisation ${(U_i, \kappa_i)}$ with transition
morphisms given by the action of $t&lt;em&gt;{ij} \in \u{G}(U_i \cap
U_j)$. We form a $G$-bundle $\pi \c E \to X$ with fibre $F$ by
gluing the trivial bundles $U_i \times F$ over each $U_i$ along the
transition maps $t&lt;/em&gt;{ij}$. (This will be possible because they come
from transitions on $\E$ and hence satisfy the cocycle condition.)
It’s clear that the sheaf of sections of $\pi$ will be isomorphic to
$\E$.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Full-faithfulness: This follows from the fact that the morphisms in
$\Bun_G(X;F)$ are determined by the automorphisms of $V_j \times F$
which appear in \ref{fibre-bundle-cat}, and the morphisms in
$\Bun&lt;em&gt;{\u{G}}(X;\u{F})$ are determined by the automorphisms of
$\F|&lt;/em&gt;{V_j}$ appearing in \ref{bundle-sheaf-cat}. Both automorphisms
determine and are determined by an element of $\u{G}(V_j)$, which
implies full-faithfulness.
\end{proof}&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So any work we do in studying $\Bun_\G(X;\F)$ for general $\G,\F$ will
in particular give results for $\Bun_G(X;F)$ for general $G,F$ as
well. As a first example we discuss “change of fibre” for bundles,
which will allow us to relate bundles with arbitrary fibre to
principal bundles. This is also known as the “associated bundle”
construction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;\begin{definition}
Let $\G$ be a sheaf of groups on $X$ and $\F$ a $\G$-sheaf. The action
of $\G$ on $\F$ is called &lt;em&gt;faithful&lt;/em&gt; if the induced morphism of
sheaves $\G \to \saut_X(\F)$ is injective.
\end{definition}&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;\begin{proposition}
Let $\G$ be a sheaf of groups on $X$ and $\F,\F’$ be two left
$\G$-sheaves. If the action of $\G$ on $\F$ is faithful, then there is
a functor
[
\Theta&lt;em&gt;{\F,\F’} \c \Bun&lt;/em&gt;\G(X;\F) \to \Bun&lt;em&gt;\G(X;\F’).
]
If the action of $\G$ on $\F’$ is also faithful then $\Theta&lt;/em&gt;{\F,\F’}$
and $\Theta_{\F’,\F}$ are quasi-inverse equivalences.
\end{proposition}&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;\begin{proof}
We first define $\Theta&lt;em&gt;{\F,\F’}$ on objects. Let $\E$ be a
$\G$-bundle on $X$ with fibre $\F$, equipped with trivialisation
${(U_i, \kappa_i)}$ and transition morphisms $\tau&lt;/em&gt;{ij} \in \G(U_i
\cap U_j)$.
\end{proof}&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Jun 2015 20:31:35 -0400</pubDate>
      <link>http://www.arponr.com/bundles-ii-comparisons</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.arponr.com/bundles-ii-comparisons</guid>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Characters in global equivariant homotopy theory</title>
      <description>
</description>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Mar 2015 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <link>http://www.arponr.com</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.arponr.com/senior-thesis</guid>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Transcendence in Infinite Jest</title>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;introduction&quot;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One needs only reach the twelfth page of &lt;em&gt;Infinite Jest&lt;/em&gt; to be
confronted with philosophy: Hal’s very first utterances express his
beliefs that “the influence of Kierkegaard on Camus is
underestimated”, that “Hobbes is just Rousseau in a dark mirror”, and
“with Hegel, that transcendence is absorption”. It is my belief that
these statements are not simply supercilious name-dropping (either on
Hal’s or David Foster Wallace’s part), but serious hints that central
aspects of the novel should be understood in a philosophical
context. This essay works towards justifying this belief using (a few
of) the remaining 1067 pages of the text, specifically focusing on
this notion of &lt;em&gt;transcendence&lt;/em&gt; which Hal immediately refers to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The notion of transcendence takes on many forms throughout philosophy,
but I think two are most relevant to understanding its form in the
novel. First we have the transcendence of existential philosophy, in
particular of Jean Paul Sartre, which is the human’s freedom and
responsibility to actively relate to, rather than be passively
determined by, its &lt;em&gt;facticity&lt;/em&gt;, the physical, social, and historical
facts which constitute it as an object in the world. Second we have
transcendentalist philosophy, which stresses the power of the isolated
individual to transcend the conformity of society, and is in part
inspired by Immanuel Kant’s concept of the individual’s
“transcendental” a priori knowledge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In what follows I argue that we may understand &lt;em&gt;Infinite Jest&lt;/em&gt;’s
philosophy of transcendence through the concept’s existential and
transcendental manifestations, and then apply this understanding to
shed a bit of light on the mystery of two characters in the novel,
Lyle and Hal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;transcendence&quot;&gt;Transcendence&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To give grounds for the relevance of existential philosophy in the
novel it suffices to consider the story at its highest level (both
geographically and conceptually), namely in Marathe and Steeply’s
discussion on America. At the center of their discourse is “freedom!
… as if it were obvious to all people what it wants to mean, this
word. But look: it is not so simple as that. Your freedom is the
freedom-&lt;em&gt;from&lt;/em&gt; … But what of the freedom-&lt;em&gt;to&lt;/em&gt;? Not just
free-&lt;em&gt;from&lt;/em&gt;. … How for the person to freely choose?”
(320). Marathe’s questions here fit very nicely into the framework of
existentialism, articulating Sartre’s conception of transcendence,
that human freedom is a responsibility, condition, and limitation in
relating to the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can interpret Marathe’s “freedom-&lt;em&gt;from&lt;/em&gt;” the world as the simplest
form of transcending facticity, understanding one’s right to
choose. Then his “freedom-&lt;em&gt;to&lt;/em&gt;” act, what he suggests is the far more
critical and difficult aspect of freedom, can be interpreted as
actually applying this right to relate with the facticity of the
world. The novel depicts the result of only exercising the former,
easier end of freedom as an ironic loss of freedom: addiction, either
to drugs or the Entertainment. The viewers who become “stuck”,
“trapped in some sort of middle”, “lost” (647) in the Entertainment
forego their role as actors in the world, and hence are reduced to
objects in the world, their facticity. This intimates one of &lt;em&gt;Infinite
Jest&lt;/em&gt;’s many double-binds: one cannot hide from the facticity of the
world in transcending one’s facticity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the novel moreover suggests that solving this existential
double-bind of transcendence lies in another form of transcendence,
namely transcendence of the self. This is expressed most clearly by
Schtitt’s basically fascist philosophy of tennis:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Tennis’s beauty’s infinite roots are self-competitive. You compete
with your own limits to transcend the self in imagination and
execution. Disappear inside the game: break through limits:
transcend: improve: win. Which is why tennis is an essentially
tragic enterprise, to improve and grow as a serious junior, with
ambitions. You seek to vanquish and transcend the limited self whose
limits make the game possible in the first place. It is tragic and
sad and chaotic and lovely. All life is the same, as citizens of the
human State: the animating limits are within, to be killed and
mourned, over and over again. (84)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here transcendence is positioned as antithetical to
transcendentalism. The “limits” one must transcend do not come from
society but from “within” the self. This opposition to
transcendentalism is made explicit when Pemulis tries to convince Hal
to take DMZ by saying that the “stuff’s original intent was to induce
what they called quote transcendent experiences in get this chronic
alcoholics”, and Hal asks in clarification, “Was it transcendent? The
term in Struck’s literature? Or was it transcendental?” Pemulis shrugs
off the difference but his next choice of words is: “some low-risk
transcendentalism with me and the Human Hatchet could be…”
(1064). This suggests that the novel attributes the degenerative
spiral of addicted, “freedom-&lt;em&gt;from&lt;/em&gt;” behavior into static facticity to
a type of transcendentalist worship of the power and rights of the
individual. Schtitt’s transcendence is instead about “vanquish[ing]”
the boundaries of the individual, embracing the “freedom-&lt;em&gt;to&lt;/em&gt;” give
oneself up to “[s]omething bigger than the self”, as Marathe says
(107).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Schtitt’s mention of the infinite and emphasis on the self as a limit
indicate a crucial link between transcendence and infinity in the
text. One such link is in the grammatical sense of the word
&lt;em&gt;infinite&lt;/em&gt;—as in a verb form not limited by tense, person, or
number—which seems to reflect Schtitt’s notion of transcendence, of
partaking in something that is not restricted by some specific subject
or time, or that “outlives you” (107). Another link lies in Avril’s
proposal that: “There are, apparently, persons who are deeply afraid
of their own emotions, particularly the painful ones. Grief, regret,
sadness. Sadness especially, perhaps. Dolores describes these persons
as afraid of obliteration, emotional engulfment. As if something truly
and thoroughly felt would have no end or bottom. Would become infinite
and engulf them” (765). So perhaps Schtitt’s “human State” can be
interpreted as simply the human state, i.e. the emotion and sentiment
which connects one to others. This is reinforced by “Hal, who’s empty
but not dumb, theoriz[ing] privately that what passes for hip cynical
transcendence of sentiment is really some kind of fear of being really
human, since to be really human (at least as he conceptualizes it) is
probably to be unavoidably sentimental and naive and goo-prone and
generally pathetic, is to be in some basic interior way forever
infantile, some sort of not-quite-right-looking infant dragging itself
anaclitically around the map, with big wet eyes and froggy-soft skin,
huge skull, gooey drool” (694–695). This last description immediately
brings Mario to mind, which fits given Mario’s close relationship with
Schtitt, complete devotion to and love of his family, and that he is
“not exactly insensitive when it comes to people” (763).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The above evinces the following picture of transcendence in &lt;em&gt;Infinite
Jest&lt;/em&gt;: the self is a boundary between and limit of the infinity of
sentiment within and the infinity of the world without, and true
transcendence is the transcendence of this boundary, the ability to
interface honestly with the world. This transcendence involves both
recognizing the inner infinity—transcending one’s facticity as a
human being with attitudes and feelings—and the outer
infinity—turning one’s transcendence on the other facticities of the
world, connecting to the human s/State. This sits in contradistinction
to trascendentalism, which the novel depicts not as the erasure of
this boundary or transcendence of this limit, but as a false, ironic
rejection of the inner emotion and pure consumption (or ingestion) of
the outer world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;lyle&quot;&gt;Lyle&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While &lt;em&gt;Infinite Jest&lt;/em&gt;’s philosophy of transcendence is best verbally
expressed by Schtitt, I believe it is best embodied by Lyle, whose
mystery is apparent from his first description:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;An oiled guru sits in yogic full lotus in Spandex and tank top. He’s
maybe forty. He’s in full lotus on top of the towel dispenser just
above the shoulder-pull station in the weight room of the Enfield
Tennis Academy, Enfield MA. … Nobody knows where he comes from or
why he’s allowed to stay, but he’s always in there, sitting yogic
about a meter off the rubberized floor of the weight room. His tank
top says TRANSCEND in silkscreen; on the back it’s got DEUS
PROVIDEBIT in Day-Glo orange. … This guru lives off the sweat of
others. Literally. The fluids and salts and fatty acids. He’s like a
beloved nut. He’s an E.T.A. institution.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If his tank top is not enough of a visual hint at his embodiment of
transcendence, his being a yogic guru described as if floating in
lotus position above the ground must be; and if it isn’t, the fact
that he later literally “hovers cross-legged just a couple mm. above
the top of the towel dispenser in the unlit weight room, eyes rolled
up white” (700) undoubtedly is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But his transcendence runs far deeper than these images. His entire
role at E.T.A. is to connect with others: “Like all good listeners, he
has a way of attending that is at once intense and assuasive: the
supplicant feels both nakedly revealed and sheltered, somehow, from
all possible judgment. It’s like he’s working as hard as you. You both
of you, briefly, feel unalone” (388). This precisely describes his
ability to transcend the boundary between his self and his
“supplicant”. He lives for and off of (the sweat of) the other. And
most strikingly, he is not an individual, but an “institution”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In light of this I want to interpret a couple of perplexing details
about Lyle. The first is his advice to Ortho Stice: “Do not
underestimate objects! Lyle says he finds it impossible to overstress
this: do &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; underestimate objects” (394). This reflects the idea
that in transcending one’s facticity, one must not disregard facticity
all together; i.e. one must actively relate to the objects in the
world to avoid getting lost in the self. This then supports the idea
that the unexplained misplacement of objects in E.T.A., including
Stice’s bed, are an attempt by James Incandenza to draw Hal out of his
self, to have Hal actually open himself to the world and its
objects. The second is the fact that the back of Lyle’s “TRANSCEND”
tank top reads “DEUS PROVIDEBIT”, i.e. “GOD WILL PROVIDE”. This hints
at the significance of faith and worship in the novel’s conception of
transcendence. This is expressed by Marathe as well: “Our attachments
are our temple, what we worship, no? What we give ourselves to, what
we invest with faith.” Lyle’s position as an essentially religious
guru points at the idea that connection between one’s honest emotions
and the infinity of the human s/State outside the self relies on an
essentially religious faith in some sort of god.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;hal&quot;&gt;Hal&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally we turn to Hal. These days the term “existential angst” evokes
the image of a clichéd sullen teenager lying in bed in a dark room,
clichéd melancholy alternative rock drowning out clichéd parental
yelling through the door. Maybe Hal isn’t so extremely clichéd but
he’s still a teenager wrestling with the idea that “inside [him]
there’s pretty much nothing at all, he knows. His Moms Avril hears her
own echoes inside him and thinks what she hears is him, and this makes
Hal feel the one thing he feels to the limit, lately: he is lonely”
(694). While it would be easy to cynically cast aside this emptiness
and loneliness as teenage naivete, &lt;em&gt;Infinite Jest&lt;/em&gt; suggests that “the
cliché ‘I don’t know who I am’ unfortunately turns out to be more than
a cliché” (204), and should be considered in the light of the serious
philosophy from which existential angst originated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Indeed, I claim that Hal’s driving struggle in the novel is the
classic existential struggle of transcending one’s facticity. Hal
specifically faces the facticity of genetics and authority: as a
“lexical prodigy” he is simply an echo of his mother, and as
“late-blooming prodigy and possible genius at tennis” he is simply an
echo of his father. Rather than actively forming his identity he is
“being encouraged to identify himself” through these echoes, acting
apparently exclusively to make his mother and in fact “every
authority-figure in his world and beyond very proud indeed”
(155). Hal’s father (as the professional conversationalist) pleads
that Hal “recognize the occasional vista beyond your own generous
Mondragonoid nose’s fleshy tip” (31)—Mondragon being Avril’s maiden
name—indicating that Hal only sees his mother in front of him, or
perhaps only interacts with the world as filtered through his
mother. This lack of identity is what gives truth for Hal to “the fact
that that the great transcendent horror is loneliness, excluded
encagement in the self” (694); he perceives his self only as a cage of
facticity which he is unable to break free of, transcend.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is why the sudden shift from third- to first-person narration of
Hal (851) is so pivotal; and why it is so important in the opening
scene of the novel that Hal believes, “I am in here” (3); and why Hal
is desperate to communicate:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I am not just a boy who plays tennis. I have an intricate
history. Experiences and feelings. I’m complex. … it transcends
the mechanics. I’m not a machine. I feel and believe. … I’m not
just a creatus, manufactured, conditioned, bred for a
function. (11–12)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The mechanics and conditioning he “transcends” are precisely his
facticity. The tragedy then is that, though he now “feel[s] and
believe[s]” in his identity, he “cannot make himself understood” (10):
“I look out. Directed my way is horror. … ‘I am not what you see and
hear.’” (12–13). Given the analysis above, Hal’s inability to
communicate his feelings with others indicates that he has not truly
transcended. While Lyle is able to bridge the infinities within and
without him, transcend himself to become an “institution” with which
others honestly connect, Hal remains stuck in his finitude, unable to
connect.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the real (but not unsatisfying) sense for me in which
&lt;em&gt;Infinite Jest&lt;/em&gt; does not finish: we are left with an incompletely
transformed, untranscended Hal, one which reflects the deep loneliness
in the incredible difficulty of both recognizing the infinity within
the self and transcending the boundary (the self) between this
infinity and the infinities of others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;references&quot;&gt;References&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;David Foster Wallace, &lt;em&gt;Infinite Jest&lt;/em&gt;, Back Bay Books, 1996.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
      <pubDate>Fri, 21 Nov 2014 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <link>http://www.arponr.com/ij-transc</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.arponr.com/ij-transc</guid>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Bundles I: definitions</title>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I decided to sit down and understand how structure groups of fibre
bundles work. Principal bundles in particular seem like fairly
ubiquitous objects, and they’ll come up right away in the upcoming
posts about bordism. So I thought I’d work through the basics
carefully and write it down.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It struck me that much of the discussion can be translated immediately
to the more general setting of sheaves, so for fun that’s how I’ll
approach things. Of course I’ll point out throughout how the more
familiar setting of bundles fits into the picture.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The aim of this first post is just to set things up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We begin by defining the motivating players advertised in the title:
bundles and structure groups.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;\begin{notation}
Fix a topological space $X$ until further notice.
\end{notation}&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;\begin{definitions}{bundles-structure-groups}
Let $F$ be a space and $G$ a topological group.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A &lt;em&gt;fibre bundle&lt;/em&gt; over $X$ with &lt;em&gt;fibre&lt;/em&gt; $F$ is a map $\pi \c E \to X$
such that there is an open cover ${U_i}$ of $X$ and homeomorphisms
$\phi_i \c \pi^{-1}(U_i) \to U_i \times F$ over $X$ for each $i$. In
particular the fibre $\pi^{-1}(x)$ is homeomorphic to $F$ for every
$x \in X$.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Such data ${(U_i,\phi_i)}$ is called a &lt;em&gt;trivialisation&lt;/em&gt; of the
fibre bundle. The &lt;em&gt;transition maps&lt;/em&gt; associated to a trivialisation
are the maps
[
t&lt;em&gt;{ij} \c U_i \cap U_j \to \aut(F),
]
where $\aut(F)$ denotes the group of homeomorphisms of $F$ with
itself, such that the automorphism $\phi_i\phi_j^{-1}$ of $(U_i \cap
U_j) \times F$ is given by $(u,f) \mapsto (u, t&lt;/em&gt;{ij}(u)(f))$.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A fibre bundle $\pi \c E \to X$ with &lt;em&gt;structure group $G$&lt;/em&gt;, or a
&lt;em&gt;$G$-bundle&lt;/em&gt;, is one where the fibre $F$ is equipped with a left
$G$-action and $\pi$ is equipped with a trivialisation for which the
transition maps $t_{ij}$ factor through the action $G \to \aut(F)$.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A $G$-bundle is &lt;em&gt;principal&lt;/em&gt; if $G$ acts simply transitively on the
fibre $F$, i.e., $F$ is homeomorphic as a left $G$-space to $G$
(which is a left $G$-space via left multiplication).
\end{definitions}&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;\begin{remark}{principal-right-action}
Note that a &lt;em&gt;trivial&lt;/em&gt; principal $G$-bundle $X \times G$ has both a
left and a right $G$-action, via left and right multiplication on $G$.
Since these two actions commute and a principal $G$-bundle $\pi \c E
\to X$ locally looks like $U \times G$ as a left $G$-space, the right
actions on $U \times G$ will glue together to give a global right
$G$-action on $E$ which preserves fibres. I.e., any principal
$G$-bundle is a right $G$-space over $X$.
\end{remark}&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are the type of objects we should have in the back of our mind
throughout. We will generalise them using the language of sheaves,
with the following definitions as our basic tools.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;\begin{definitions}
Let $\G$ be a sheaf of groups on $X$.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A &lt;em&gt;$\G$-sheaf&lt;/em&gt; on $X$ is a sheaf of sets $\E$ on $X$ together with
a right action $\E \times \G \to \E$ of $\G$. A &lt;em&gt;morphism of
$\G$-sheaves&lt;/em&gt; $\E \to \E’$ on $X$ is a morphism of sheaves of sets
which commutes with the $\G$-actions.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A &lt;em&gt;$\G$-pseudotorsor&lt;/em&gt; is $\G$-sheaf $\E$ such that for all $U
\subseteq X$ open, either $\E(U)$ is empty or the action of $\G(U)$
on $\E(U)$ is simply transitive. A $\G$-pseudotorsor $\E$ is a
&lt;em&gt;$\G$-torsor&lt;/em&gt; if moreover $\E(U_i)$ is nonempty for all $i$ in some
open cover ${U_i}$ of $X$. A &lt;em&gt;morphism of $\G$-pseudotorsors or
$\G$-torsors&lt;/em&gt; is simply a morphism of the underlying $\G$-sheaves.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;There is a &lt;em&gt;trivial $\G$-torsor&lt;/em&gt; on $X$ given by $\G$ equipped with
the action given by right multiplication. A $\G$-sheaf $\E$ is
called &lt;em&gt;trivial&lt;/em&gt; if there is an isomorphism of $\G$-sheaves $\E \iso
\G$.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Note that if $\E$ is a $\G$-sheaf, then $\E|&lt;em&gt;U$ is a $\G|_U$-sheaf
on $U$ for any $U \subseteq X$. If $P$ is some property which can be
enjoyed by $\H$-sheaves on $Y$ for any sheaf of groups $\H$ on any
space $Y$—e.g. the properties of being a pseudotorsor, or torsor,
or trivial—then we say a $\G$-sheaf $\E$ on $X$ *locally has the
property* $P$ if the $\G|&lt;/em&gt;{U_i}$ sheaf $\E|_{U_i}$ has the property
$P$ for all $i$ in some open cover ${U_i}$ of $X$. The same goes
for morphisms of $\G$-sheaves.
\end{definitions}&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;\begin{remark}
Note we should really have called these &lt;em&gt;right&lt;/em&gt; $\G$-sheaves,
$\G$-pseudotorsors, and $\G$-torsors. Of course we can analogously
define &lt;em&gt;left&lt;/em&gt; $\G$-sheaves, $\G$-pseudotorsors, and $\G$-torsors. We
will need to distinguish between the two later on (as we needed to
distinguish between left and right $G$-spaces for bundles above), but
until then we agree to leave the modifier “right” implicit.
\end{remark}&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;\begin{remarks}{torsor-equiv}
Observe that any morphism of $\G$-torsors is an isomorphism, since
clearly it must locally be an isomorphism. So suppose $\E$ is a
$\G$-pseudotorsor with a section $s \in \E(U)$ for some $U \subseteq
X$ open. Then there is a morphism of $\G|_U$-torsors $\G|_U \to \E|_U$
on $U$ given by
[
\G(V) \ni 1 \mapsto s|_V \in \E(V), \quad V \subseteq U\text{ open}.
]
As just observed this must an isomorphism. I.e., any global section
trivialises a pseudotorsor, and in particilar a pseudotorsor is a
torsor if and only if it is locally trivial. In fact, any $\G$-sheaf
is a $\G$-torsor if and only if it’s locally trivial. This is
immediate from the preceding discussion and the following lemma, that
being a pseudotorsor or torsor is a local condition.
\end{remarks}&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;\begin{lemma}{torsor-local}
If a $\G$-sheaf $\E$ on $X$ is locally a $\G$-pseudotorsor
(resp. $\G$-torsor), then $\E$ is a $\G$-pseudotorsor
(resp. $\G$-torsor).
\end{lemma}&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;\begin{proof}
It’s clear that the statement for $\G$-torsors follows immediately
from the statement for pseudotorsors, so we need only prove the
latter. Assume $\E|&lt;em&gt;{U_i}$ is a $\G|&lt;/em&gt;{U_i}$-pseudotorsor for all $i$
in an open cover ${U_i}$ of $X$. Let $V \subseteq X$ such that
$\E(V)$ is nonempty. Let $s, t \in \E(V)$. We need to show there is a
unique $g \in \G(V)$ such that $t = sg$. Write
[
V_i \ce V \cap U_i, \quad V&lt;em&gt;{ij} \ce V \cap U_i \cap U_j,
]
[
s_i \ce s|&lt;/em&gt;{V_i}, \quad s&lt;em&gt;{ij} \ce s|&lt;/em&gt;{V&lt;em&gt;{ij}}, \quad t_i \ce
t|&lt;/em&gt;{V_i}, \quad t&lt;em&gt;{ij} \ce t|&lt;/em&gt;{V&lt;em&gt;{ij}}
]
for all $i,j$ where these
intersections are nonempty. Since $\E|&lt;/em&gt;{U_i}$ is a
$\G|&lt;em&gt;{U_i}$-pseudotorsor, there is a unique $g_i \in \G(V_i)$ such
that $t_i = s_ig_i$; then
[
s&lt;/em&gt;{ij}g_i|&lt;em&gt;{V&lt;/em&gt;{ij}} = t&lt;em&gt;{ij} = s&lt;/em&gt;{ij}g_j|&lt;em&gt;{V&lt;/em&gt;{ij}},
]
so uniqueness also implies $g_i|&lt;em&gt;{V&lt;/em&gt;{ij}} = g_j|&lt;em&gt;{V&lt;/em&gt;{ij}}$. Since the
$V_i$ cover $V$, the $g_i$ glue to $g \in \G(V)$. The equation $t =
sg$ holds when restricted to each $V_i$ and thus must hold on $V$, and
the uniqueness of $g$ is immediate from the uniqueness of the $g_i$.
\end{proof}&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s bring things back down to bundles for a second.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;\begin{definition}{map-sheaf}
To any space $Y$ we can associate a sheaf of sets $\u{Y}$ on $X$: the
&lt;em&gt;sheaf of continuous maps to $Y$&lt;/em&gt;, given by the assignment
[
U \mapsto \hom_\Top(U,Y), \quad U \subseteq X \text{ open}.
]
\end{definition}&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;\begin{example}{bundle-example}
Let $G$ be a topological group. Then $\u{G}$ is in fact a sheaf of
groups. If $\pi \c E \to X$ is a right $G$-space over $X$ (a space
over $X$ with a right $G$-action preserving fibres) then the sheaf
$\E$ of continuous sections of $\pi$ is a $\u{G}$-sheaf in a canonical
manner. By \ref{principal-right-action}, any principal $G$-bundle
gives an example of such a $\pi \c E \to X$. In this case we will
moreover have that $\E$ is locally trivial, and hence a $\u{G}$-torsor
by \ref{torsor-equiv}.
\end{example}&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We next generalise the main definitions we began with in
\ref{bundles-structure-groups}. I’m not sure if there’s standard
terminology for some of these things so I’m just sticking with the
terminology for fibre bundles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;\begin{definition}
If $\E$ is a sheaf of sets on $X$ then we have a &lt;em&gt;sheaf of
automorphisms&lt;/em&gt; $\saut_X(\E)$ on $X$ which to every open $U \subseteq
X$ assigns the set $\aut(\E|_U)$ of isomorphisms $\E|_U \to \E|_U$
of sheaves on $U$.
\end{definition}&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;\begin{remark}
If $G$ is a topological group and $F$ a space then giving a $G$-action
on a space $F$ is equivalent to giving a continuous map $G \to
\aut(F)$. Observe similarly that if $\G$ is a sheaf of groups on
$X$ and $\F$ a sheaf of sets on $X$ then giving a left $\G$-action on
$\F$ is equivalent to giving a morphism of sheaves $\G \to
\saut_X(\E)$.
\end{remark}&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;\begin{definition}{bundle-sheaf}
Let $\F$ be a sheaf of sets on $X$ and $\G$ a sheaf of groups on $X$.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A &lt;em&gt;bundle&lt;/em&gt; over $X$ with &lt;em&gt;fibre&lt;/em&gt; $\F$ is a sheaf of sets $\E$ on $X$
such that there is an open cover ${U_i}$ of $X$ and isomorphisms
$\phi_i \c \E|&lt;em&gt;{U_i} \to \F|&lt;/em&gt;{U_i}$ for each $i$.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Such data ${(U_i,\phi_i)}$ is called a &lt;em&gt;trivialisation&lt;/em&gt; of the
bundle. The &lt;em&gt;transition morpshisms&lt;/em&gt; associated to a trivialisation
are the automorphisms $t&lt;em&gt;{ij} \ce \phi_i\phi_j^{-1}$ of $\F|&lt;/em&gt;{U_i
\cap U_j}$.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A bundle $\E$ on $X$ with &lt;em&gt;structure group $\G$&lt;/em&gt;, or a
&lt;em&gt;$\G$-bundle&lt;/em&gt;, is one where the fibre $\F$ is equipped with a left
$\G$-action and $\E$ is equipped with a trivialisation for which the
transition morphisms $t_{ij}$ lie in the image of $\G(U_i \cap U_j)
\to \saut_X(\F)(U_i \cap U_j)$.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A $\G$-bundle is &lt;em&gt;principal&lt;/em&gt; if $\F$ is isomorphic as a left
$\G$-sheaf to $\G$ (which is a left $\G$-sheaf via left
multiplication).
\end{definition}&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In fact we could have left that last definition out, since according
to \ref{principal-equals-torsor} below, we have already defined it!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;\begin{lemma}{auto-left}
Let $\G$ be a sheaf of groups on $X$. Any morphism of right
$\G$-sheaves $t \c \G \to \G$ is given by left multiplication by some
$g \in \G(X)$:
[
t_U \c\  \G(U) \ni h \mapsto g|_Uh \in \G(U), \quad U \subseteq X \text{
open}.
]
\end{lemma}&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;\begin{proof}
Let $1_U \in \G(U)$ denote the unit for $U \subseteq X$ open. Let $g
\ce t_X(1_X) \in \G(X)$. Since $1_X|_U = 1_U$ and $t$ is a morphism of
right $\G$-sheaves we have for any $U \subseteq X$ open and $h \in
\G(U)$:
[
t_U(h) = t_U(1_U) \cdot h = t_X(1_X)|_U \cdot h = g|_Uh.
]
\end{proof}&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;\begin{proposition}{principal-equals-torsor}
Let $\G$ be a sheaf of groups on $X$. A sheaf of sets $\E$ on $X$ is a
principal $\G$-bundle if and only if it is a right $\G$-torsor.
\end{proposition}&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;\begin{proof}
($\Rightarrow$) Let $\E$ be a principal $\G$-bundle sheaf. So we have
an open cover ${U_i}$ of $X$ and isomorphisms $\E|&lt;em&gt;{U_i} \iso
\G|&lt;/em&gt;{U_i}$ such that the transition morphisms $t&lt;em&gt;{ij}$ are given by
left multiplication by some $g&lt;/em&gt;{ij} \in \G(U_i \cap U_j)$. Since left
and right multiplication commute, the right actions of $\G|&lt;em&gt;{U_i}$ on
$\E|&lt;/em&gt;{U_i}$ via right-multiplication will glue together to give a
global right action of $\G$ on $\E$ (this is precisely analogous to
\ref{principal-right-action}). Thus $\E$ is a right $\G$-sheaf, and
since $\E$ is by construction locally trivial it must be a $\G$-torsor
by \ref{torsor-equiv}.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;($\Leftarrow$) Suppose $\E$ is a right $\G$-torsor. By
\ref{torsor-equiv} it is locally trivial: there is an open cover
${U_i}$ of $X$ and isomorphisms of right $\G$-sheaves $\E|&lt;em&gt;{U_i}
\iso \G|&lt;/em&gt;{U_i}$. So $\E$ is a bundle sheaf with fibre $\G$. Then that
$\E$ has structure group $\G$ is immediate from \ref{auto-left}.
\end{proof}&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, I’ve said that we’ve &lt;em&gt;generalised&lt;/em&gt; the notion of fibre bundle
with this notion of bundles as sheaves. But we’ve been proceeding on
analogies alone. So though I’ve hinted at it in \ref{bundle-example},
I haven’t actually proved in what sense this is a generalisation. But
I’ll save that for the next post.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
      <pubDate>Mon, 16 Jun 2014 17:10:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <link>http://www.arponr.com/bundles-i-definitions</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.arponr.com/bundles-i-definitions</guid>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Vector fields and the J-homomorphism</title>
      <description>
</description>
      <pubDate>Fri, 09 May 2014 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <link>http://www.arponr.com</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.arponr.com/vfields</guid>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Defining the cotangent complex</title>
      <description>
</description>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Dec 2013 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <link>http://www.arponr.com</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.arponr.com/quillen-cotangent</guid>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Dold-Kan correspondence</title>
      <description>
</description>
      <pubDate>Sat, 26 Oct 2013 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <link>http://www.arponr.com</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.arponr.com/doldkan</guid>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Numbers at Google</title>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This is a post about some numbers that I saw at work one day during my
internship at Google. I present them to you without further ado.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;21:&lt;/strong&gt; I got to run a job with 21 terabytes of input. &lt;em&gt;Tera&lt;/em&gt;. And
that’s compressed.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;10000000000:&lt;/strong&gt; 21 TB means I got to compute statistics on data
sets of size greater than 10 billion. &lt;em&gt;Billion&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;3:&lt;/strong&gt; It took fewer than 3 hours to run that job. I love MapReduce
and resources.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;23:&lt;/strong&gt; Later on, after realising I had made some stupid mistakes, I
needed to run that job again (and because it felt so damn cool the
first time, and I could, so why not). Anyway it turns out the data
was on some machines on the East Coast, and the job was running on
machines on the West Coast. That’s efficiency. Well so I (and, by
“I”, I mean someone else on my team who actually knew what he was
doing) managed to get the job running next door to the data. And for
ten minutes or so, that 21 TB was being sent to the job at more than
23 gigbatyes per second. &lt;em&gt;Giga&lt;/em&gt;. Holy bandwidth, batman.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So it turns out working at Google indeed has perks. Those numbers are
all due to some really smart people that work (or have worked)
here. That’s nice to think about. It’s even nicer to stop thinking
about that, look at those numbers, and just feel dope as hell, if
only for a moment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perhaps two moments, though. A new number arrived the following day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;30:&lt;/strong&gt; After tweaking some things, the job ran in less than 30
minutes. That’s some astounding stuff.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 Aug 2013 22:40:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <link>http://www.arponr.com/numbers-at-google</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.arponr.com/numbers-at-google</guid>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
