<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>arponr</title>
    <description>blog by arpon</description>
    <link>http://www.arponr.com</link>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 19 Jan 2015 14:01:13 -0500</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://www.arponr.com/feed.xml" rel="self"/>
    
    <item>
      <title>Numbers at Google</title>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This is a post about some numbers that I saw at work one day during my
internship at Google. I present them to you without further ado.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;21:&lt;/strong&gt; I got to run a job with 21 terabytes of input. &lt;em&gt;Tera&lt;/em&gt;. And
        that’s compressed.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;10000000000:&lt;/strong&gt; 21 TB means I got to compute statistics on data
                 sets of size greater than 10 billion. &lt;em&gt;Billion&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;3:&lt;/strong&gt; It took fewer than 3 hours to run that job. I love MapReduce
       and resources.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;23:&lt;/strong&gt; Later on, after realising I had made some stupid mistakes, I
        needed to run that job again (and because it felt so damn
        cool the first time, and I could, so why not). Anyway it
        turns out the data was on some machines on the East Coast,
        and the job was running on machines on the West
        Coast. That’s efficiency. Well so I (and, by “I”, I mean
        someone else on my team who actually knew what he was doing)
        managed to get the job running next door to the data. And
        for ten minutes or so, that 21 TB was being sent to the job
        at more than 23 gigbatyes per second. &lt;em&gt;Giga&lt;/em&gt;. Holy
        bandwidth, batman.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So it turns out working at Google indeed has perks. Those numbers are
all due to some really smart people that work (or have worked)
here. That’s nice to think about. It’s even nicer to stop thinking
about that, look at those numbers, and just feel dope as hell, if
only for a moment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perhaps two moments, though. A new number arrived the following day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;30:&lt;/strong&gt; After tweaking some things, the job ran in less than 30
        minutes. That’s some astounding stuff.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 Aug 2013 22:40:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <link>http://www.arponr.com/numbers-at-google</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.arponr.com/numbers-at-google</guid>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
