<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Prose on Arpon Raksit</title>
    <link>https://arponr.github.io/kajerna/prose/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Prose on Arpon Raksit</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 24 Nov 2024 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://arponr.github.io/kajerna/prose/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>A wolf</title>
      <link>https://arponr.github.io/kajerna/prose/wolf/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 24 Nov 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://arponr.github.io/kajerna/prose/wolf/</guid>
      <description>A wolf would only come so close to you if it hadn&amp;rsquo;t noticed your presence. You may wonder how that could come to be; you likely have a belief in you, deep and from long ago, that wolves are equipped with keen senses. There is evidence that supports that belief, but there are other matters to be considered too. How was the wind? It has been so windy here recently. People keep bringing it up in my vicinity as they greet one another, and then they look outside together at the gusting leaves, and then they look back at each other with concern and understanding.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>River fish</title>
      <link>https://arponr.github.io/kajerna/prose/river-fish/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 19 Oct 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://arponr.github.io/kajerna/prose/river-fish/</guid>
      <description>He kept going to the river. When there, he would sit on a pier or crouch by the bank, and he would start moving into a meditation, when suddenly, in the corner of an eye, in the half of the corner that was still open, he would sense the shadow of a fish jumping out of and then back into the water. He would then open his eyes fully, and he would search the water for some time, but no other fish would appear.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>NOTICE: further work around Feld Hall</title>
      <link>https://arponr.github.io/kajerna/prose/fuld/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 15 Apr 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://arponr.github.io/kajerna/prose/fuld/</guid>
      <description>Good morning, Institute community,&#xA;Thank you for your continued accommodation during this period of spring renovation on our campus. As the tree excision and path retiling have been completed without incident and according to schedule, the work will advance as planned.&#xA;In the coming days, there will be significant person removal activity around Feld Hall. We will carry on doing our best to limit disruption to our campus. Several persons around Feld Hall, D Building, A Building, and B Building have lived quite long with managed care and regular maintenance.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Radiator</title>
      <link>https://arponr.github.io/kajerna/prose/radiator/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Feb 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://arponr.github.io/kajerna/prose/radiator/</guid>
      <description>The temperature is well below freezing, and the property manager has notified their tenants that the heating systems in their buildings cannot help but operate less efficiently in the present conditions. That must be the reason for my hearing, from inside the radiator: the violent bubbling of an unwatched stew; the desparate knocking of thousands of tiny gnomes; a tennis match greatly complicated by the nonstandard, coiled geometry of the court; the lurching of a vessel, like a boat or a stomach, at sea; a child slipping down the stairs; an alien turning to sludge in an unfavorable environment; a jazz drummer alone.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Memory</title>
      <link>https://arponr.github.io/kajerna/prose/memory/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 23 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://arponr.github.io/kajerna/prose/memory/</guid>
      <description>These were supposed to be the lines that came to me earlier in the day, when I was feeling deeply about the ordinary. But those lines have since escaped me. They were plain lines, like these, but they were also sublime, as I saw that moment, as opposed to these more muted lines. That is what I seem to be able to recall.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A boulder</title>
      <link>https://arponr.github.io/kajerna/prose/boulder/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 10 Oct 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://arponr.github.io/kajerna/prose/boulder/</guid>
      <description>How did I get here? I ask myself, struggling to contend with the boulder atop me and the Earth below, each exerting their natural forces. I have only a ragged memory of what came before this&amp;mdash;a pleasant stroll on the mountain, a little hunger&amp;hellip; And then? I am at a loss. It all feels inappropriate.&#xA;The sun is rising or setting and the wind is weaving through the tree line or being wrung from my body.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>To wit</title>
      <link>https://arponr.github.io/kajerna/prose/wit/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Sep 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://arponr.github.io/kajerna/prose/wit/</guid>
      <description>Our ancestors would utter things like, What do you wot of that traveller?&#xA;The verb there is to wit, synonymous with to know, but with an especially mischievous set of conjugations: present tense wot, present participle witting, past tense and past participle wist.&#xA;(The word does survive in our times in the adverbial phrase to wit, though, to my understanding, this is employed exclusively in legal contexts or in affecting a hoity-toity attitude.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>By the window</title>
      <link>https://arponr.github.io/kajerna/prose/window/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 31 Aug 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://arponr.github.io/kajerna/prose/window/</guid>
      <description>A question By the window, I look out blankly to a perched bird as I listen to the music, and a question returns to me: What do you think it is in music that moves you? A pianist posed the question to me recently, and it has returned to me more than once. Or rather, what leads these returns is an inaccuracy I&amp;rsquo;ve recognized in the response I gave; still, the question itself follows along too.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Empty</title>
      <link>https://arponr.github.io/kajerna/prose/empty/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 16 Aug 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://arponr.github.io/kajerna/prose/empty/</guid>
      <description>The space in the home had initially been empty, but a clutter accumulated over the years. Perhaps it was the bookshelves that were first installed: text required notation, hence required purchase. It did not take long for the collection to spill beyond the shelves. The desk was introduced when it was realized that some kind of office was needed in the home, to cordon off the working mind, and an additional lamp, chair, and couch then became necessary to enable shifts in disposition during rumination.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The young man who might still be</title>
      <link>https://arponr.github.io/kajerna/prose/might-still-be/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 Sep 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://arponr.github.io/kajerna/prose/might-still-be/</guid>
      <description>The young man was at a party in a ballroom. He might still be. That&amp;rsquo;s the beginning and end of this story.&#xA;He wore a requisitely nice white shirt and black pants. A dark grey tie hung firmly around his neck and gleaming black shoes kept him just off the floor. He pulled off his suit jacket when he noticed he was warm, rolled and rumpled up his sleeves when later he began to sweat.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Metro North</title>
      <link>https://arponr.github.io/kajerna/prose/metro-north/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Sep 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://arponr.github.io/kajerna/prose/metro-north/</guid>
      <description>You&amp;rsquo;re on the Metro North Railroad, travelling from Grand Central Station to Stamford, CT, seated facing the rear of the train, neck twisted towards the window on your left. You slip in your earbuds and welcome that Irish genius&amp;rsquo;s crooning into your blood. Your eyes open and close as the old train wobbles leisurely out of the dim tunnel.&#xA;The darkness continues into the city air, the night creeping into day as summer tapers away.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The insect and the M.D.</title>
      <link>https://arponr.github.io/kajerna/prose/insect-md/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Jul 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://arponr.github.io/kajerna/prose/insect-md/</guid>
      <description>It&amp;rsquo;s two o&amp;rsquo;clock in the suburban afternoon. A grey sky hangs low outside, whispering in the back of everyone&amp;rsquo;s mind re looming rainfall. Miscellaneous questions are caught in the whispers and whirl forward into consciousness—Are the cushions on the patio chairs out? Does the garden need to be humanly watered?—landing one after another in a paralyzing mess—Should that errand be run now or postponed until the rain has passed?—like piles of crisp dead leaves you&amp;rsquo;ve tucked against the curb being scattered back over your lawn by gusts of wind.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Transcendence in Infinite Jest</title>
      <link>https://arponr.github.io/kajerna/prose/ij/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 21 Nov 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://arponr.github.io/kajerna/prose/ij/</guid>
      <description>Introduction One needs only reach the twelfth page of Infinite Jest1 to be confronted with philosophy: Hal&amp;rsquo;s very first utterances express his beliefs that &amp;ldquo;the influence of Kierkegaard on Camus is underestimated&amp;rdquo;, that &amp;ldquo;Hobbes is just Rousseau in a dark mirror&amp;rdquo;, and &amp;ldquo;with Hegel, that transcendence is absorption&amp;rdquo;. It is my belief that these statements are not simply supercilious name-dropping (either on Hal&amp;rsquo;s or David Foster Wallace&amp;rsquo;s part), but serious hints that central aspects of the novel should be understood in a philosophical context.</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
